<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://mdaisuke.net/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://mdaisuke.net/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-12-01T12:17:36+00:00</updated><id>https://mdaisuke.net/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Daisuke Miyazaki’s Blog</title><author><name>[{&quot;name&quot;=&gt;&quot;Daisuke Miyazaki&quot;}, {&quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;daisuke.miyazaki012@gmail.com&quot;}]</name></author><entry xml:lang="jp"><title type="html">夕暮れや</title><link href="https://mdaisuke.net/jp/2025/10/27/%E5%A4%95%E6%9A%AE%E3%82%8C%E3%81%AE%E9%9D%92%E6%A9%99/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="夕暮れや" /><published>2025-10-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-10-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mdaisuke.net/jp/2025/10/27/%E5%A4%95%E6%9A%AE%E3%82%8C%E3%81%AE%E9%9D%92%E6%A9%99</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mdaisuke.net/jp/2025/10/27/%E5%A4%95%E6%9A%AE%E3%82%8C%E3%81%AE%E9%9D%92%E6%A9%99/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/poems/2025-10-27%20poem.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;夕暮れの空&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;my-16 flex justify-center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;font-serif text-lg tracking-[0.2em] leading-[3rem] text-gray-700 dark:text-gray-300 h-72&quot; style=&quot;writing-mode: vertical-rl;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;夕暮れや&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;青橙を&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;裂かん雲&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;波の向こうに&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;地這い星かな&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>[{&quot;name&quot;=&gt;&quot;Daisuke Miyazaki&quot;}, {&quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;daisuke.miyazaki012@gmail.com&quot;}]</name></author><category term="jp" /><summary type="html">2025年霜降の一句</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">How Walking to Get More Exercise Led to an Insight About Intellectual Productivity and an App Idea</title><link href="https://mdaisuke.net/en/2025/09/17/sanpou-issue/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How Walking to Get More Exercise Led to an Insight About Intellectual Productivity and an App Idea" /><published>2025-09-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-09-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mdaisuke.net/en/2025/09/17/sanpou-issue</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mdaisuke.net/en/2025/09/17/sanpou-issue/">&lt;h3 id=&quot;it-started-with-a-lack-of-exercise&quot;&gt;It Started with a Lack of Exercise&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It all began with a common problem: I wasn’t getting enough exercise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remote work became standard, which was flexible, but it also meant I had days where I didn’t leave the house at all. I knew I needed to change that, so I started a new habit: just walking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After about a year of this, I noticed something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don’t really hit your step goals by just wandering aimlessly. To get a high step count, you need to be intentional. You have to consciously decide, “Okay, I’m leaving my desk,” and then go outside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This regular habit of “leaving the desk” became a starting point for a new question and a new “problem” for me to solve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-hypothesis-good-ideas-happen-away-from-the-desk&quot;&gt;The Hypothesis: “Good Ideas Happen Away from the Desk”&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re in a period of change, with some companies pushing for a “return to the office.” But setting those trends aside, I decided to seriously analyze a feeling I was having.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was something I’d often felt as an engineer: “My thoughts seem to get more organized when I walk or step away from my computer.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This led me to a hypothesis:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Are new ideas and organized thoughts born not while sitting at the desk, but in the moments away from it?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what I started to call my “Sanpou no Issue” (The “Walk” Issue).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This line of thinking led to two more questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Is this just a personal quirk?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Or does everyone eventually reach this same conclusion?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I can find an answer, this “project” of mine will be complete.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-core-of-intellectual-production-in-the-age-of-genai&quot;&gt;The Core of Intellectual Production in the Age of GenAI&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pursuing this “Sanpou Issue” led me to think about the essence of intellectual production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, the core of this is &lt;strong&gt;“the process of breaking down information in my own words and truly internalizing it.”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the recent rise of Generative AI, this concept has become more important than ever. In an age where an AI can instantly create “plausible-sounding” text, &lt;strong&gt;“how quickly you can capture your own unique thoughts as written text”&lt;/strong&gt; directly affects your personal productivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An AI cannot yet generate the “original insights” that come from your specific experiences and perspective. In fact, the value of those original insights has only increased.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-problem-idle-time-vs-capture-time&quot;&gt;The Problem: “Idle” Time vs. “Capture” Time&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, how do we generate more of these original insights?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my experience, it’s during “idle” or “zoning out” (ぼーっとする) time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means no music, no podcasts, and no apps. Just thinking. Walking turned out to be the perfect environment for this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this creates a major problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An idea is useless if you can’t &lt;strong&gt;immediately write it down&lt;/strong&gt; in a usable format.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carrying a paper notebook is one solution, but it’s often inconvenient. It’s a hassle to pull out a pen and notebook while you’re walking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But using your standard, full-featured note app isn’t the right tool for this moment, either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You open the app, decide which folder to use, wait for the editor to load… and in those few seconds, the initial momentum of the idea is lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-solution-a-ux-focused-only-on-the-moment-of-capture&quot;&gt;The Solution: A UX Focused Only on the “Moment of Capture”&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone uses a note app these days, whether it’s Notion, Evernote, or just a basic memo pad. I’m not asking people to switch from their favorite tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final organization and editing of notes can, and should, still be done in those main apps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I saw a need for was a “wrapper” for these existing apps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to design a UX (User Experience) that is specialized for &lt;strong&gt;one thing only: “The exact moment an idea appears, allowing you to write it down immediately.”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It launches instantly to a blank text input.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There are no extra features or formatting.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The text can be easily sent to your main note app later.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And most importantly: &lt;strong&gt;Data never leaves the device (local-first).&lt;/strong&gt; Your private “fragments of thought” are not uploaded to any server.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;in-closing&quot;&gt;In Closing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A simple habit I started for exercise has, in a roundabout way, led me to think about intellectual production, the challenge of capturing thought, and a concept for an app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thinking away from the desk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And capturing the idea the moment it appears.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This simple process might be the key skill we need to work effectively in the new era of AI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This question I call the “Sanpou no Issue” isn’t fully answered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But don’t you also find yourself “thinking” while you walk?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.apple.com/jp/app/sanpou/id6749672561?uo=2&quot;&gt;link to the sanpou app&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>[{&quot;name&quot;=&gt;&quot;Daisuke Miyazaki&quot;}, {&quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;daisuke.miyazaki012@gmail.com&quot;}]</name></author><category term="en" /><summary type="html">A simple habit I started for exercise has, in a roundabout way, led me to think about intellectual production, the challenge of capturing thought, and a concept for an app.</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="jp"><title type="html">運動不足解消の「散歩」が、なぜ「知的生産」と「専用ノートアプリ」のアイデアに行き着いたか</title><link href="https://mdaisuke.net/jp/2025/09/16/sanpou-issue/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="運動不足解消の「散歩」が、なぜ「知的生産」と「専用ノートアプリ」のアイデアに行き着いたか" /><published>2025-09-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-09-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mdaisuke.net/jp/2025/09/16/sanpou-issue</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mdaisuke.net/jp/2025/09/16/sanpou-issue/">&lt;h3 id=&quot;すべての始まりは運動不足だった&quot;&gt;すべての始まりは「運動不足」だった&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;すべては、多くの現代人が抱えるであろう単純な悩み「運動不足」から始まりました。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;パンデミックによる在宅勤務の定着は、私たちの働き方に柔軟性をもたらしましたが、同時に「一歩も外に出ない日」を生み出しました。このままではいけない。そう思い、私はひとつの習慣を始めました。それは、ただ「歩く」ことです。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;この習慣を一年ほど続けてみて、気づいたことがあります。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;漫然と歩くだけでは、目標の歩数を稼ぐことは意外と難しい。歩数を稼ぐためには、「よし、歩こう」と意識的に机を離れ、外に出るという「積極的な行動」が必要だったのです。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;この「机を離れる」という行為を習慣化するプロセス。それが、私にとっての「きっかけ作り」となり、そして新たな「悩み」と「問い」の始まりでもありました。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;仮説アイデアは机以外で生まれる&quot;&gt;仮説：「アイデアは、机以外で生まれる」&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;パンデミックを経て、働き方はオンラインとオフラインに分かれ、今また「オフィス回帰」のような揺り戻しも起きています。そんな環境の変化はさておき、私は自分自身に起きた「ある現象」と真っ向から向き合うことにしました。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;それは、「散歩したり、机を離れたりすると、考えが整理される」という、エンジニアとしても昔からよく経験していた感覚です。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ここに、私は一つの仮説を立てました。
&lt;strong&gt;「アイデアの『種』や思考の『整理』は、PCの前に座っている時ではなく、そこから離れた場所でこそ生まれるのではないか？」&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;これが、私の中で「Sanpouのイシュー（散歩の課題）」と名付けたプロジェクトの始まりです。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;この問いの先に、二つの疑問が続きます。
「この感覚は、自分特有のものなのか？」
「それとも、程度の差こそあれ、皆も同じ結論に行き着くものなのか？」&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;もし、この答えが出れば、このプロジェクトは一つの区切りを迎えます。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;生成ai時代に問われる知的生産の本質&quot;&gt;生成AI時代に問われる「知的生産の本質」&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;この「Sanpouのイシュー」を突き詰めていくと、知的生産の本質にぶつかります。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;私にとっての知的生産の本質とは、&lt;strong&gt;「インプットした情報を、自分の言葉で噛み砕き、自分の中に落とし込む行為」&lt;/strong&gt;そのものです。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;そして、生成AIが大衆化した今、この本質はさらに重要な意味を持ち始めました。AIが一瞬で「それらしい」文章を生成できる時代だからこそ、&lt;strong&gt;「自分自身のユニークな思考や発見を、いかに早く『書いた言葉（テキスト）』として固定化できるか」&lt;/strong&gt;が、個人の生産性に直結するのです。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AIはまだ、あなたが体験したことや、あなた独自の視点から生まれる「一次の気づき」を生み出すことはできません。その価値は、むしろ高まっています。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ぼーっとする時間と書き留める技術&quot;&gt;「ぼーっとする」時間と「書き留める」技術&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;では、どうすればその「一次の気づき」は生まれやすくなるのか。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;私の経験則では、それは「ぼーっとする」時間です。
音楽やラジオ、もちろんSNSアプリも使わず、ただ自分の頭だけで考える。散歩は、そのための最適な「装置」でした。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;しかし、ここで最大のジレンマが発生します。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;せっかく浮かんだアイデアも、それを「使える形式」にまで持っていくには、&lt;strong&gt;即座に「書いた言葉」としてテキストに落とし込むことが不可欠&lt;/strong&gt;です。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;紙のノートや手帳を持ち歩くのも一つの手ですが、デジタルの便利さに慣れた現代人にとって、それは不便でもあります。歩きながらペンとノートを取り出すのは、なかなかの重労働です。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;かといって、普段使っている多機能なノートアプリを起動するのも、違います。
アプリを開き、どのノートブックに入れるか考え、リッチテキストエディタが立ち上がるのを待つ…。その数秒の間に、せっかくのアイデアの「輝き」は失われてしまいます。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;結論アイデアが生まれた瞬間に特化したux&quot;&gt;結論：アイデアが「生まれた瞬間」に特化したUX&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;この時代、誰もが何かしらのノートアプリ（Notion, Evernote, メモ帳…）を使っています。私は、彼らに「今すぐそれをやめて、これに切り替えてくれ」と言いたいわけではありません。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;最終的にノートを整理し、体系化するのは、これまで通りPCやスマホで、お気に入りのアプリでやってもらえばいいのです。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;私が作りたかったのは、それら既存アプリの「ラッパー」として機能するものです。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;「アイデアが脳裏に浮かんだ、その瞬間。その勢いのまま、書き殴るところまで」&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;これだけに特化したUX（ユーザー体験）を設計できないか。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;起動したら、即、入力画面。&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;余計な機能は一切ない。&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;書いたテキストは、後で簡単にメインのノートアプリに転送できる。&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;そして何より、&lt;strong&gt;データは一切デバイスから外に出ない（ローカルファースト）&lt;/strong&gt;。自分の「思考の断片」という最もプライベートな情報を、誰にも渡さない。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;おわりに&quot;&gt;おわりに&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;運動不足を解消するために始めた散歩という習慣が、巡り巡って「知的生産の本質」と「現代における思考のキャプチャ方法」という問い、そして一つのアプリの構想にまで繋がりました。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;机を離れて考える。
そして、浮かんだ瞬間を逃さず書き留める。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;このシンプルな行為こそが、AIと共存するこれからの時代を生き抜く、私たち人間の「武器」になるのではないか。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;この「Sanpouのイシュー」という名の問いは、まだ終わりません。
あなたも、歩きながら「考えて」いませんか？&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.apple.com/jp/app/sanpou/id6749672561?uo=2&quot;&gt;sanpouアプリのリンクはこちら&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>[{&quot;name&quot;=&gt;&quot;Daisuke Miyazaki&quot;}, {&quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;daisuke.miyazaki012@gmail.com&quot;}]</name></author><category term="jp" /><summary type="html">運動不足解消のために始めた散歩が、巡り巡って「知的生産の本質」と「現代における思考のキャプチャ方法」という問い、そして一つのアプリの構想にまで繋がった経緯を綴ります。</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">The Art of Forgetting in this Information Society</title><link href="https://mdaisuke.net/en/2025/08/18/art-of-forgetting/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Art of Forgetting in this Information Society" /><published>2025-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mdaisuke.net/en/2025/08/18/art-of-forgetting</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mdaisuke.net/en/2025/08/18/art-of-forgetting/">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Humans are happy creatures because they can forget.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a phrase my math teacher taught me when I was a student. At the time, I didn’t think much of it, but in today’s world, where information constantly floods us, I deeply feel the weight of these words. This isn’t just a philosophical question; it’s an extremely practical wisdom for maintaining mental and physical health and having the space to think in this information society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every day, we are exposed to an enormous amount of information: work tasks, news, social media and app notifications, personal notes. If we tried to remember everything, our brains would quickly become overwhelmed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, “intentionally forgetting” can be seen as a skill that can be learned. To forget with peace of mind, there must be a trust that we can “recall it anytime.” “Forgetting” and “recalling when needed” are two sides of the same coin, and creating a “system” for this is essential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The simplest and most powerful practical example of this is the act of writing a diary or a notebook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing down thoughts and information from your mind. This act itself is a process of detaching information from the brain and consciously “forgetting” it. However, simply writing it down is not enough. If you need that information later, it’s meaningless if you can’t find it quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why searchability is also essential. The concept of Evergreen Notes is full of hints for this. “Being able to forget” is not a weakness; it should be a strong boost to living wisely and happily in this information society.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>[{&quot;name&quot;=&gt;&quot;Daisuke Miyazaki&quot;}, {&quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;daisuke.miyazaki012@gmail.com&quot;}]</name></author><category term="en" /><summary type="html">An architecture of being able to forget matters in this information society.</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="jp"><title type="html">忘れられる仕組み作り</title><link href="https://mdaisuke.net/jp/2025/08/18/art-of-forgetting/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="忘れられる仕組み作り" /><published>2025-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mdaisuke.net/jp/2025/08/18/art-of-forgetting</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mdaisuke.net/jp/2025/08/18/art-of-forgetting/">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;「人間は忘れられるから幸せな生き物なのです」&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;これは、学生時代の数学の先生が教えてくれた言葉です。当時は深く考えませんでしたが、情報が絶え間なく押し寄せる現代において、この言葉が持つ意味の重さを実感しています。これは単なる哲学的な問いではなく、情報社会で心身の健康を保ち、考えるゆとりを持つための、極めて実践的な知恵ではないでしょうか。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;私たちは日々、膨大な情報に晒されています。仕事のタスク、ニュース、SNSやアプリの通知、個人的なメモ。すべてを覚えておこうとすれば、脳はすぐにパンクしてしまうでしょう。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ここで「意図的に忘れる」ことは技術であり、学ぶことができるのではないでしょうか。安心して忘れるためには、「いつでも思い出せる」という信頼がなければなりません。「忘れる」ことと、必要な時に「思い出せる」ことは表裏一体であり、そのための「仕組み」を作ることが不可欠です。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;その最もシンプルで強力な実践例が、日記やノートを書くという行為です。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;頭の中にある思考や情報を書き出す。この行為そのものが、脳から情報を切り離し、意識的に「忘れる」プロセスです。しかし、ただ書き出すだけでは不十分です。後からその情報が必要になった時、すぐに見つけ出せなければ意味がありません。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;だからこそ、検索性を意識した工夫が求められます。Evergreen Noteの考え方にはそのヒントが詰まっています。「忘れられる」ことは弱さではなく、情報社会を賢く幸せに生き抜く後押しになるはずです。&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>[{&quot;name&quot;=&gt;&quot;Daisuke Miyazaki&quot;}, {&quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;daisuke.miyazaki012@gmail.com&quot;}]</name></author><category term="jp" /><summary type="html">この情報社会で考えるゆとりを持つためのヒントは、忘れられる仕組みづくり。</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">We Must Not Delegate Understanding</title><link href="https://mdaisuke.net/en/2025/07/02/we-must-not-delegate-understanding/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="We Must Not Delegate Understanding" /><published>2025-07-02T15:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-02T15:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mdaisuke.net/en/2025/07/02/we-must-not-delegate-understanding</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mdaisuke.net/en/2025/07/02/we-must-not-delegate-understanding/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/dont delegate understandings.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;dont delegate understandings&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generative AI has become capable of telling sophisticated lies indistinguishable from human ones.
Precisely because of such an era we must not delegate “understanding” itself to AI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gathering and interpreting information in our own way and putting it into your own words has become ever crucial. Because without it, connecting disparate knowledge and experiences to form a single thread, will be impossible.
This act of “connecting the dots” is the essence of thought: a domain that must never be delegated to others let alone AI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what should we do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the easies starting points would be keeping a diary.
Record daily events and feelings in your own words as they are.
And instead of just writing and forgetting, repeatedly look back at past notes, ideas and records. This would allow us to connect with memos from other notes at unexpected moments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your thoughts will make progress, by facing your notes and continuously updating them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe we must find time in our daily lives to continue these activities.
Otherwise we will fall into intellectual stagnation and its worst case, be unable to move forward.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>[{&quot;name&quot;=&gt;&quot;Daisuke Miyazaki&quot;}, {&quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;daisuke.miyazaki012@gmail.com&quot;}]</name></author><category term="en" /><summary type="html">In an era where generative AI can tell sophisticated lies, we must not delegate the act of thinking and connecting dots in our own words.</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="jp"><title type="html">理解を委任してはいけない</title><link href="https://mdaisuke.net/jp/2025/07/02/understanding-delegation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="理解を委任してはいけない" /><published>2025-07-02T15:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-02T15:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mdaisuke.net/jp/2025/07/02/understanding-delegation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mdaisuke.net/jp/2025/07/02/understanding-delegation/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/dont delegate understandings.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;dont delegate understandings&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;生成AIは、人間と見分けがつかないほど巧みな嘘をつけるようになった。
そんな時代だからこそ僕たちは、「理解」そのものをAIに委任してはいけない。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;情報を集め、自分なりに解釈し、言葉にする。
そしてバラバラに見える知識や経験をつなぎ合わせ、一つの線にしていく
この「点と点を繋ぐ」作業こそ思考の本質であり
決して他者に、ましてやAIに委任してはならない領域だ。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ではどうすればいいのか。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;簡単なことから始めるなら、まずは日記じゃないだろうか。
日々の出来事や感じたことをありのまま自分の言葉で記録する。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;次に、ただ書きっぱなしにするのではなく、何度も過去のノートを振り返ること。
書かれたアイデアや記録が、別のノートのメモとふとした瞬間に結びつくことがある。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;そうしてノートと向き合い更新し続けることで思考は深まっていく。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;こうした営みを、日々のわずかな時間で見つけて続ける。
そうでなければ僕たちは思考停止に陥り、前へ進むことはできないだろう。&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>[{&quot;name&quot;=&gt;&quot;Daisuke Miyazaki&quot;}, {&quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;daisuke.miyazaki012@gmail.com&quot;}]</name></author><category term="jp" /><summary type="html">生成AIが巧みな嘘をつける時代だからこそ、自分の言葉で思考し、点と点をつなぐ作業を委任してはならない。日記やノートを通じて思考を深める重要性について。</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="jp"><title type="html">夏が始まった</title><link href="https://mdaisuke.net/jp/2025/06/16/%E5%A4%8F%E3%81%8C%E5%A7%8B%E3%81%BE%E3%81%A3%E3%81%9F/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="夏が始まった" /><published>2025-06-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-06-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mdaisuke.net/jp/2025/06/16/%E5%A4%8F%E3%81%8C%E5%A7%8B%E3%81%BE%E3%81%A3%E3%81%9F</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mdaisuke.net/jp/2025/06/16/%E5%A4%8F%E3%81%8C%E5%A7%8B%E3%81%BE%E3%81%A3%E3%81%9F/">&lt;!-- ここに写真追加 --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2025-06-16 夏が始まった.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;窓とソファの写真&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;暑い、晴れていて空梅雨。&lt;br /&gt;
エアコンをつけているとどうしても機械音ばかり。&lt;br /&gt;
耐えられなくはないくらいの温度なので全体的に窓を開けて風通りをよくしてみている。&lt;br /&gt;
気持ちがいいくらい緑が窓から見える。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;自分で作った机の上&lt;br /&gt;
窓越しでちょうどいい高さにあってpcをおいて作業できる。&lt;br /&gt;
自分の家の中で好きな場所があれば帰ってきたくなる。&lt;br /&gt;
清澄亭で庭の横で作業していたことを思い出す。&lt;br /&gt;
緑のカーテン。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;play-audio-on-hover&quot; style=&quot;cursor:pointer; text-decoration:underline;&quot;&gt;氷が揺れて器にあたる音&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
ひんやりとしたグラス。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;夏が始まった。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;audio id=&quot;hover-audio&quot; src=&quot;/assets/audio/2025-06-16 夏の音.webm&quot;&gt;&lt;/audio&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
document.addEventListener(&apos;DOMContentLoaded&apos;, function() {
  const trigger = document.querySelector(&apos;.play-audio-on-hover&apos;);
  const audio = document.getElementById(&apos;hover-audio&apos;);
  if (trigger &amp;&amp; audio) {
    trigger.addEventListener(&apos;mouseenter&apos;, () =&gt; {
      audio.currentTime = 0;
      audio.play();
    });
    trigger.addEventListener(&apos;mouseleave&apos;, () =&gt; {
      audio.pause();
      audio.currentTime = 0;
    });
  }
});
&lt;/script&gt;</content><author><name>[{&quot;name&quot;=&gt;&quot;Daisuke Miyazaki&quot;}, {&quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;daisuke.miyazaki012@gmail.com&quot;}]</name></author><category term="jp" /><summary type="html">氷が揺れて器にあたる音</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="jp"><title type="html">obsidianを使い始めて1年レビュー</title><link href="https://mdaisuke.net/jp/2025/03/20/obsidian%E3%82%92%E4%BD%BF%E3%81%84%E5%A7%8B%E3%82%81%E3%81%A61%E5%B9%B4%E3%83%AC%E3%83%93%E3%83%A5%E3%83%BC/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="obsidianを使い始めて1年レビュー" /><published>2025-03-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mdaisuke.net/jp/2025/03/20/obsidian%E3%82%92%E4%BD%BF%E3%81%84%E5%A7%8B%E3%82%81%E3%81%A61%E5%B9%B4%E3%83%AC%E3%83%93%E3%83%A5%E3%83%BC</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mdaisuke.net/jp/2025/03/20/obsidian%E3%82%92%E4%BD%BF%E3%81%84%E5%A7%8B%E3%82%81%E3%81%A61%E5%B9%B4%E3%83%AC%E3%83%93%E3%83%A5%E3%83%BC/">&lt;p&gt;ObsidianはEvergreen notesの原則にのっとってできたノートアプリ。これまでのPKM(personal knowledge manegement)にはAppleのNotesをつかっており、乗り換えてみてからもう早一年以上経つので、レビューしてみる。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;メモを増やしても自分の考え方が深まらない。どこか深まって整理がついても、ノートがうまくまとまらない。でもまとまる時間もない。他にも細かい課題があった。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;このアプリを使い方を学び始めてからいろんな発見があった。1年以上経ち、もっと自由に考えられるようになったと思う。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;考えることは、今を知れば未来がわかるような線形的な形でないこと。振り返りと書き直しを重ねて考えを広げたり深めたりできること。そして知識の探索の幅はどれだけ広くても良いこと。まさに点と点を繋ぐような体験こそ考えを深めることなんだと、ノートが洗練されるたびに感じた。ノートに向き合う時間が習慣になったと思う。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ここではとっつきやすく、Notesでも続けていた日記を例にあげてみる。日記は固有なノートの集まりとして使っている。obsidianの自由度が高さを活かして、自分にあった形に最適化できる。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;いま日常のノートは以下のように組んでいる。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;朝/夜の気分&lt;/strong&gt;: 感覚で天気マークをつけている。幸せでいられているか。メタデータとして保存する。変化に気づくために、他のノートで一覧化したりできる。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;天気&lt;/strong&gt;: APIで自動で取得している、気分と強い相関があることも。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;タスク&lt;/strong&gt;: 保存庫中のノートでチェックボックスに変換+実施予定日をいれると、毎日ノートに表示される。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;固有ノート&lt;/strong&gt;: 日常を最も小さな単位で切り取った書き下ろし。素であり、RAWであり、まとまってないことがほとんど。書き下ろしてから、大体タイトルをつける。思いついたらとりあえず書く。ホットキーを設定して一コマンドで開けるようにするとなお便利。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;振り返り&lt;/strong&gt;: その日最後の固有ノート。あったこと、印象に残ったこと、仕事で寝かせたい考えの書き殴り、あった人などざっくばらんに書き留める。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Task、Templater、unique note creatorあたりのプラグインを使っている。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;また活字を読んだら書き留める場所として、AIを使い倒すための書き溜める場所として、そしてプレゼンを作る場所として、、といろんな活用の方法があるが、これはまた次のポストで扱うとする。&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>[{&quot;name&quot;=&gt;&quot;Daisuke Miyazaki&quot;}, {&quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;daisuke.miyazaki012@gmail.com&quot;}]</name></author><category term="jp" /><summary type="html">ObsidianはEvergreen notesの原則にのっとってできたノートアプリ。これまでのPKM(personal knowledge manegement)にはAppleのNotesをつかっていたが課題があり、乗り換えてみてからもう早一年以上経つので、レビューしてみる。</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="jp"><title type="html">IPadを手放した</title><link href="https://mdaisuke.net/jp/2025/03/17/ipad%E3%82%92%E6%89%8B%E6%94%BE%E3%81%97%E3%81%9F/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="IPadを手放した" /><published>2025-03-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mdaisuke.net/jp/2025/03/17/ipad%E3%82%92%E6%89%8B%E6%94%BE%E3%81%97%E3%81%9F</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mdaisuke.net/jp/2025/03/17/ipad%E3%82%92%E6%89%8B%E6%94%BE%E3%81%97%E3%81%9F/">&lt;p&gt;iPadを手放した。出先でIPhoneをPCとして使う工夫をしている。結局ipadですらジャケットのポケットには入らない。端末自体の演算力やバッテリーの持ちは十分だ。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;折りたたみキーボードがあれば手慣れた速度感でノートと向き合うことができる。ここではコーヒーを飲み切るくらいの時間を区切りの目安にするまとまれば成果物としても十分、まとまらないとそれは逆に煮詰まりすぎ、スコープが大きすぎる可能性がある。共有まで含めて、docmentでも大体のアプリがスマホ対応しているわけだし、web対応もしているので発信まで含めても終えられる。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;また、スタンド等も必要。iphone自体を傾けないと姿勢が保てずに体験が悪化するので。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;一枚のノートを軽く、小さく区切りながら細かくまとめるには、道具の準備もすぐできる方が良い。ポケットに忍ばせられるくらいの大きさであれば手軽だし、折りたたみキーボードは開いただけで接続されるものもあり手短だ。&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>[{&quot;name&quot;=&gt;&quot;Daisuke Miyazaki&quot;}, {&quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;daisuke.miyazaki012@gmail.com&quot;}]</name></author><category term="jp" /><summary type="html">結局iPadですらジャケットのポケットには入らない。スマホの演算力やバッテリーの持ちは今や十分。</summary></entry></feed>