<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://mdaisuke.net/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://mdaisuke.net/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-01-20T04:41:25+00:00</updated><id>https://mdaisuke.net/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Daisuke Miyazaki’s Blog</title><author><name>[{&quot;name&quot;=&gt;&quot;Daisuke Miyazaki&quot;}, {&quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;daisuke.miyazaki012@gmail.com&quot;}]</name></author><entry xml:lang="jp"><title type="html">ワークベンチv2</title><link href="https://mdaisuke.net/jp/2025/01/13/%E3%83%AF%E3%83%BC%E3%82%AF%E3%83%99%E3%83%B3%E3%83%81/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ワークベンチv2" /><published>2025-01-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mdaisuke.net/jp/2025/01/13/%E3%83%AF%E3%83%BC%E3%82%AF%E3%83%99%E3%83%B3%E3%83%81</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mdaisuke.net/jp/2025/01/13/%E3%83%AF%E3%83%BC%E3%82%AF%E3%83%99%E3%83%B3%E3%83%81/">&lt;div id=&quot;photo-scroll&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; src=&quot;/assets/js/photoScroll/index.build.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</content><author><name>[{&quot;name&quot;=&gt;&quot;Daisuke Miyazaki&quot;}, {&quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;daisuke.miyazaki012@gmail.com&quot;}]</name></author><category term="jp" /><summary type="html">DIY！アート愛好者の妻へ特製ワークベンチをプレゼント。どこにも売っていない特別なワークベンチを作る挑戦をしてみました。その一部始終を書き下ろしてみました。</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">The Droplet</title><link href="https://mdaisuke.net/en/2023/09/02/droplet/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Droplet" /><published>2023-09-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-09-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mdaisuke.net/en/2023/09/02/droplet</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mdaisuke.net/en/2023/09/02/droplet/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/story/droplet.png&quot; class=&quot;image_in_post&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;In the year 15 of the solar calendar (2065 AD).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to the worst-case scenario of the global warming prediction for 2050, in mid-2047, the United Nations headquarters issued a statement that swift and unprecedented global cooperation was necessary. As part of this effort, Japan adopted a new era name after in 2050, which was shared with the rest of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was commuting from the unchanged Hanzomon Line. Slightly sleep-deprived, but it was already mid-October. I walked in the clear weather until I reached the nearest station. At Otemachi Station where I got off, it was connected underground, so once I arrived at the station, I couldn’t see outside until reaching to the office. A crowd of unchanged people. Just following the person in front of me. Before I knew it, I was sitting at my desk at the company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My desk happens to be by the window of this building. It’s a 28-story high-rise, but our company is on the 4th floor, so there’s not much of a view to speak of. My logged-in computer had accumulated emails from clients, so I started going through them one by one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the early afternoon, a black lightning bolt struck Tokyo Station. By the time I finished going through the emails and the subsequent meetings, the clock had struck 1:00. When I looked out the window, the outside seemed somewhat dim, and the sky visible through the gaps in the buildings was tinged with gray.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/story/droplet_man_in_the_building.JPG&quot; class=&quot;image_in_post&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- Work with colleagues --&gt;
&lt;!-- Spend a day feeling negative due to customer trouble --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Why is it that even in this day and age, emails are still such a pain? Why haven’t we introduced a chat app?”&lt;br /&gt;
“Well, there are a lot of old-fashioned clients we deal with, you know. The sales department and the managers have apparently explained it to them many times, but they’re used to doing everything by email, so they don’t listen to anything else.”&lt;br /&gt;
“I see… So it’s what they call precedent-based thinking?”&lt;br /&gt;
“Exactly. I’ve heard that it’s becoming less common in the world, but there are still a lot of places like that, aren’t there?”&lt;br /&gt;
“That’s too bad.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s true that many of our clients are old companies that have been around for decades. We also have many long-standing relationships that date back to before the change of era. It’s frustrating to think that we’re still wasting time on something that’s not essential like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Well, there’s nothing we can do about it.”&lt;br /&gt;
“Yeah, I guess not.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wonder when it started, but it’s become such a common phrase. I can’t help but have a negative attitude when faced with situations like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/story/droplet_subway.png&quot; class=&quot;image_in_post&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the train ride home, I was pushed around by a sea of people. As usual, during peak hours on the Hanzomon Line, hundreds of thousands of people pass through each day, and the interior of the train has hardly changed since I first rode it when I was born in the year of the sun calendar. When I’m spacing out, my eyes catch the advertising panel in the train car that hasn’t changed much either. Today, just like any other day, the usual weather forecast was playing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only thing that seems to have changed is the futuristic production vibes that show seems to wrap itself with. This country really hasn’t changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- AI caster says there will be an event using battery storage due to the expected shortfall in the country&apos;s power supply, and a solar panel satellite will fly. --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“A panda was born at Urashima Kindergarten and is attracting attention.”&lt;br /&gt;
“Up Everybody Technology Co., Ltd., a drone startup, has been listed on the first section of the Tokyo Stock Exchange.”&lt;br /&gt;
“Due to the expected shortfall in power supply again today, the droplet is expected to be observed in Toyosu, Chofu, and Tama River. Please cooperate in conserving electricity.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s the same old thing. I’ve gotten used to it, but unfortunately, I can’t see the panda or the droplet from inside this subway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the Toyosu Bridge, people who had been caught in the rain were seen here and there. A couple with a child, a high school student, and a man wearing work clothes and glasses. The adjacent high-rise buildings continue to shine brightly and illuminate Tokyo. The high school student and the man in work clothes seem to be moving forward with only their bodies while being absorbed in their smartphones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the traffic signal on the road, the indicator stays in the middle. In the solar calendar, a globally standardized protocol was implemented to reflect the world’s intentions to save energy. Policies were promoted to visualize city-wide power information in the infrastructure. In Japan, one of the remnants of the previous administration’s policy, are the indicators implemented inside each traffic signal. Because of this, people can see the remaining power of the entire city everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A child walking along the roadside of a large bridge looks uneasy and looks around in all directions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Mom, what’s the name of this river?” The mother looked at the river he was pointing to and answered, “This river is the Sumida River. This bridge was built to cross that river.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He looked down at the river with keen interest and casually continued.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Mom, what would happen if I jumped off from here?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She looked at the railing he was pointing to and answered,
“It’s dangerous, so you shouldn’t do it. You could get seriously hurt if you jump off the bridge.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He looked slightly disappointed, but took their hand off the railing after hearing her words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Mom, what’s that building?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She looked at the building he was pointing to and answered,
“A lot of people work in that building.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Hmmm… Mom, what’s that?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She looked up to where he was pointing. After a moment, she said,
“That’s called a ‘droplet.’ It transports the electricity we use.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/story/droplet.png&quot; class=&quot;image_in_post&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something small and shining could be seen gradually descending towards them. More than 40 years have passed since the competition in battery technology heated up around the year 2020. It has become possible to store a large amount of power in solid-state batteries made of ultra-light carbon. These objects, resembling shooting stars, are massive batteries. To minimize air resistance for rapid delivery, they are shaped like droplets, hence the name was coined by the citizens. A single droplet can supply power to 10,000 households.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The droplet falls rapidly before opening a parachute to decelerate. The dandelion-fluff-like tip, known as the “Flower,” seems to be attached to extend the flight distance while slowing down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The droplet slows down gradually while blooming its “Flower,” finally landing on a waiting ship far away. The ship anchors at the nearest riverbank, and the droplet is blinking in a faint red color. The anchored droplet looked like a breathing flower on the river.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To the child, the red blinking seemed somewhat familiar, and he turned their gaze away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Oh, you’re already bored?”&lt;br /&gt;
“I’m hungry.”&lt;br /&gt;
“Yes it’s getting late, let’s go home and eat something yummy.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The city’s power supply began, and a lightning bolt sign was displayed on the signal indicator at the far end of the bridge. The city seemed no different; it was the same old Tokyo flowing along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/story/droplet_signal.png&quot; class=&quot;image_in_post&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, only one of the three indicators next to the traffic light is illuminated. When these indicators first began lighting up as the system was introduced to infrastructure, people felt anxious as the gauge lowered. There were even conspiracy theories suggesting that the government was using this sense of urgency to curb power consumption. There was also news making headlines that power wouldn’t actually run out even if the indicator went out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In reality, there had never been a blackout or any such incidents. This system, which has already become a part of daily life, seamlessly integrated into society within just a few years, and it no longer becomes a topic of discussion, just like the air around us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Today’s power consumption level is ‘critical.’ Please cooperate in conserving energy.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An unremarkable weather forecast announcer still delivers this now-familiar phrase. The display panel on today’s Hanzomon Line train hasn’t changed a bit from 20 years ago. Not paying any attention to the news, I was listening to Japanese music that has recently revitalized. There are a few people holding umbrellas in the car, where a sort of damp, musty feeling hangs in the air. It’s raining outside. But before I know it, I’m being drawn back into the building again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I finally finished preparing the documents and, before I realized it, it had gotten dark outside. The lights were on outside the building as usual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was idly staring out the window. Suddenly, everything except the screen of my PC went pitch black. The lights that filled the buildings around me went out in an instant. Glancing hurriedly towards my colleague who sits at the back, I could vaguely see his face illuminated by his PC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Wait, is this a blackout??”&lt;br /&gt;
“Are you okay?”&lt;br /&gt;
“…I can’t connect to the internet either. This is bad.”&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was eerily quiet. An unsettling silence I had never experienced before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The traffic lights at the intersection, the lighting in small stores, and even the sparkling neon signs—all vanished in an instant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/story/droplet_blackout.png&quot; class=&quot;image_in_post&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had no idea where to look.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Um, I think the door might not open, too?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, that silence didn’t last long. Soon after, cries of surprise and honking of car horns filled the air outside, and I could hear people scrambling and whispering in the darkness. I noticed that there seemed to be some sort of commotion going on behind the door.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking outside, I saw people on the sidewalk turning on their phone lights, shaking them gently to illuminate their surroundings. At the far-off intersection, the traffic lights were out. A taxi parked a little ahead seemed lost, unsure of which direction to proceed in. The building across the street, usually blandly lit by fluorescent lights, was now completely dark and unrecognizable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“…Should we go outside?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recognized a few people afar going downstairs. I felt sorry for those who are working on higher floors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I went outside, I saw a few people walking around in suits, flicking their smartphone lights. Just like when my colleague’s face was illuminated earlier, the only source of light as far as I could see was from people holding smartphones. I realized how expansive the area outside the building, usually taken for granted, actually was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought we could only wait for the electricity to come back on. Then I looked up at the sky and was astonished. Tiny lights filled the sky completely. It reminded me of the time when, over five years ago, I saw the droplets in Tokyo’s sky for the first time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But on closer inspection, the lights were stationary. Each one was fixed in place. I was taken aback when I realized these weren’t the droplets, but the light of actual stars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Wait, could these be stars?”&lt;br /&gt;
“Hey, this is really bad!”&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I heard my colleague’s voice who had come down. Turning around, his face was also lit up just like the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“No, look at this.”&lt;br /&gt;
“Oh, did you figure something out?”&lt;br /&gt;
“No, not that…“&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I pointed to the sky. His face, illuminated by the smartphone, looked puzzled,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Huh? Wow, that’s a lot of droplets… wait, what?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a moment, the silence returned. The light that had been illuminating the road ahead was gone. The voices of the people who had come down from the building, the noise all around, everything went quiet. Everyone seemed to be looking up at the sky. They couldn’t take their eyes off of the stationary lights filling the sky, instead of the moving ones they all expected to see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/story/droplet_finale.png&quot; class=&quot;image_in_post&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fleeting anxiety I felt at that moment has disappeared somewhere, and I can’t remember how much time has passed since then. What I do remember is the impassioned voice of someone who shouted, “It’s the droplets!” and the faint yet clearly audible sigh of relief that seemed to echo between the buildings afterward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, three years later, I sometimes think back to that moment as I sit at my blurry fourth-floor desk. Things seem to have changed, and yet, nothing has actually changed.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>[{&quot;name&quot;=&gt;&quot;Daisuke Miyazaki&quot;}, {&quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;daisuke.miyazaki012@gmail.com&quot;}]</name></author><category term="en" /><summary type="html">Due to the worst-case scenario of the global warming prediction for 2050, in mid-2047, the United Nations headquarters issued a statement that swift and unprecedented global cooperation was necessary. As part of this effort, Japan adopted a new era name after in 2050, which was shared with the rest of the world.</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="jp"><title type="html">雫</title><link href="https://mdaisuke.net/jp/2023/09/02/%E9%9B%AB/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="雫" /><published>2023-09-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-09-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mdaisuke.net/jp/2023/09/02/%E9%9B%AB</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mdaisuke.net/jp/2023/09/02/%E9%9B%AB/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/story/droplet.png&quot; class=&quot;mx-auto my-4&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;陽暦15年(西暦2065年)のこと。&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;地球温暖化予想2050年シナリオは最悪のケースをたどったため、2047年中旬、国連総本部は迅速かつこれまでにない世界的な協力が必要と声明を表示した。日本はその一環として新しい年号を定め、2050年より年号を改める方針を打ち出し、世界中の共通年号として共有された。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ぼくは、なにも変わらない半蔵門線から出勤していた。若干寝不足気味であったが、もう10月中旬である。最寄り駅に着くまでは快晴の中を歩いた。降りた大手町駅では地下つながりになっているので、一度駅についたら最後、オフィスに着くまでは外の様子はわからない。変わらぬ人の群。前の人をただ体が追っていくだけ。気づいたときには、会社のデスクに座っていた。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- 変わらない日常を描く --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;自分のデスクはたまたま、このビルの窓際にある。28階立ての高層ビルであるがうちの企業は4階なので、とりわけいい景色が見えるわけでもない。ログインしたパソコンには客先からのメールが溜まっていたので、一つずつ捌いていく。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;昼過ぎに、黒い稲妻が東京駅を襲った。やっとこさ捌き切ったメールと続いた会議から一息をついたときには時計の針は13時を刺していた。ふと窓の外を見ると、なんとなく外が薄暗く、ビルの隙間からみえる空が灰色がかっていた。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/story/droplet_man_in_the_building.JPG&quot; class=&quot;mx-auto my-4&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- 同僚との仕事 --&gt;
&lt;!-- 顧客トラブルがあって後ろ向きな日を過ごす --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;「この時代になってもまだメールなんて骨が折れるよ、チャットアプリをなんでうちは導入していないわけ？」&lt;br /&gt;
「どこまでいってもうちのお客さんには古いところが多いからさ。営業部門や責任者も何度も説明しにいったらしいんだけれど、うちはずっとメールでやってきたから問題なかったんだの一点貼りで聞かないところが多いんだってさ」&lt;br /&gt;
「はあ。。。。いわゆる前例主義ってやつ？」&lt;br /&gt;
「そうそう。もう世間ではだいぶ少なくなったって聞いてるけど、結局そういうところって多いんじゃないの？」&lt;br /&gt;
「残念だねえ」&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;たしかにうちのお客様にはこのみち何十年、という古い会社が多い。年号が変わる前からの付き合いも多い。そうしてこうやって何か本質的でないものに今日も時間が割かれているのは嫌なものだ。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;「まあしゃあないよ」&lt;br /&gt;
「しゃあないね」&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;いつからだろうか、仕方ないがこんなに口癖になったのは。後ろ向きな姿勢にならざるをえないのであった。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- その日の夜、 雲が上がって--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/story/droplet_subway.png&quot; class=&quot;mx-auto my-4&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;帰りの電車では、人の波に揉まれる。相変わらずにして半蔵門線のピークタイムはこの4, 50年同じように何十万人という人を1日に捌いているのである。陽暦前に生まれた自分がこの電車にのっていたときから、ほとんど形が変わっていない車内の広告パネル。ぼーっとしていると目がパネルを捉える。今日も日々のニュースが流れていた、お決まりの天気予報である。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;変わってしまったことといえば、なんとなく未来感のある演出くらいである。この国は本当に変わらない。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- 国としての電力残口が下回る予定で、電池蓄電池によるイベントがあるでしょうとAIキャスター --&gt;
&lt;!-- 太陽光パネル衛星が飛ぶ --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;「浦島幼稚園でパンダのこどもが生まれ、注目を集めています。」&lt;br /&gt;「東証一部へ、ドローンのスタートアップを展開しているアップエブリバディテクノロジー株式会社が上場しました。」&lt;br /&gt;「本日も電力残口が下回る予想のため、豊洲、調布、多摩川で雫の観測が予想されます。節電にご協力ください。」&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;相変わらずの様子である。もう慣れっこになってしまったが、残念ながらパンダも雫もこの地下鉄の中からは見ることはできない。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;豊洲大橋では、ちらほらと雨に懲りた人が散見された。子連れのカップル、高校生と作業服をきたメガネをかけた男性。隣接する高層ビルは変わらなく煌々と輝きながら東京を照らしている。高校生と作業服の男性は、スマホに夢中になりながら体だけが意思を持って前に進んでいるようにもみえる。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;道路の信号で、インジゲーターが残り中となっている。陽暦では世界的意向を反映すべく国際的に標準のプロトコルが反映され、各国のインフラに電力情報が可視化されるよう政策が推し進められた。日本では前政権からの名残の一つで、各信号にはこのインジゲーターが実装された。町のあらゆるところで都市全体残りの電力を見ることができる。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- バッテリーパックがパラシュートで降りてくる --&gt;
&lt;!-- 夜は流れ星に見えるイベント --&gt;
&lt;!-- とくに見上げることなく慣れてしまう親子、たまにこどもが気づくくらい --&gt;
&lt;!-- 気候変動で日照、エネルギー予測ができなくなった世界、応急処置としてバッテリーパックがピンポイントで届くようになった --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;大きな橋の道脇を歩くこどもは、落ち着かない様子で四方八方を見ている。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;「ママ、この川はなんて名前なの？」
母親はこどもが指差す川を見て、答えた。
「この川は隅田川だよ。この橋はその川を渡るために作られたんだよ。」&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;こどもは興味津々で、川を見下ろしながら何気なく続けた。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;「ママ、ここから飛び降りたらどうなるの？」&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;母親はこどもが指差す欄干を見て、答えた。
「それは危ないからやめておいた方がいいよ。橋の上から飛び降りると大怪我をするかもしれないからね。」&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;こどもは少し残念そうな表情を浮かべたが、母親の言葉を聞いて欄干から手を離した。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;「ママ、あの建物は何？」&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;母親はこどもが指差す建物を見て、答えた。
「あの建物にはではね、たくさんの人が働いているんだよ。」&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;「ふーん。。。。ママ、あれはなに？」&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;質問ぜめにするこどもの指に、お母さんは顔を上げる。少し時間がたってから、お母さんは言った。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- 湧く様子をもう少し具体的に書く --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;「あれは雫っていうの。私たちがつかう電気を運んでいるのよ」&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/story/droplet.png&quot; class=&quot;mx-auto my-4&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;小さく光り輝くものが少しずつこちらに降ってくるのが見える。充電技術の競争が激化し始めた2020年あたりから40年以上が経った今、超軽量カーボンで作った固形電池に多量の電力を貯蔵することが可能となった。流れ星にみえるこの物体は巨大な充電池で、迅速な供給を目指した空気抵抗を最小化するため、雫の形をしている。それに伴って名前がついたのだ。雫一つで、1万世帯分の電力を賄うことができる。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;雫は急速に落下してからパラシュートを開き減速する。たんぽぽの綿毛の形を模倣して作られた先端部分は花と呼ばれ、減速しながら飛行距離を伸ばすためについているらしい。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;雫は少しずつ花をさかせながら減速し、遠くで待機する船の上に降り立った。船は最も近くにある河岸に泊まり、雫は淡い赤色をまとっては点滅している。川に停まった雫は呼吸をする花のようだった。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;こどもからしたら赤く点滅している様子は何か見慣れてるようで、外方を向いた。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;「あら、もう飽きちゃったの？」&lt;br /&gt;
「ぼく、お腹空いた」&lt;br /&gt;
「もう遅いもんね。早くかえって美味しいものたべようね」&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;街の給電が始まり、はるかむこうの橋の終端にある信号機のインジゲーターにも稲妻のサインが表示された。街の様子は至って変わらず、いつもの東京が流れていた。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- ある日、雫が届かないトラブルが発生する --&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/story/droplet_signal.png&quot; class=&quot;mx-auto my-4&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;今日は、信号機の横にもあるサインのインジゲーターは3本のうち1つのみしか点灯していない。普及が始まってインジゲーターが点灯し始めた当時は、ゲージが少なくなると人は不安感に苛まれていた。政府はこの焦燥感を利用して、電力消費を抑えようとするという陰謀説も流れたりした。また、実際にはインジゲーターが切れても電力は枯渇しないというニュースも話題となった。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;実情としては、実際にはまた停電などは一度も起きなかったこともなかった。すでに日常に溶け込んだこの仕組みはわずか数年のうち世の中と当たり前に溶け込み、なんでもない空気のように話題にあがることもなくなった。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;「本日の電力消費量は「厳しい」です。節電にご協力ください。」&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;もはや慣れすぎてしまったこの文言を、あいかわらず取り柄のない天気予報のアナウンサーが言う。なんでもなく流れる今日の半蔵門線のパネルは、20年前のそれと一向に変わっていない。&lt;!-- 気にしない主人公  --&gt;何を気にすることもなく、ぼくは最近元気になってきた邦楽を聞いている。なんとなく湿っぽいこもった感じが漂う車内には、傘をもつ人もちらほらいる。外は雨が降っていた。でも気がついたら、またビルの中に吸い込まれていくのだ。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;資料作りがやっと終わり、ふと気がつくと外は暗くなり、いつものなんてことのないビル外に灯りがともっている。遠目でぼやっと外を見やっていたそのとき、突然、目の前のPC以外が真っ暗になった。ビル群を敷き詰められた明かりは一瞬のうちに光を失った。奥の方に座る同僚のほうをハッと見やると、PCで彼の顔あたりがぼやっと照らされているのがわかる。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;「え、ちょっと停電ですか？？？」&lt;br /&gt;
「大丈夫？」&lt;br /&gt;
「…ちょっとネットも繋がらないんだけれど。やばい」&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;静かすぎる。聞いたことのない静寂はどこか落ち着かない。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;交差点の信号、小さな店舗の照明、ともすればきらめくネオン看板も、すべてが一瞬にして消え去った。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/story/droplet_blackout.png&quot; class=&quot;mx-auto my-4&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;どこを見ればいいのかわからない。
「ちょっとドアも開かないんじゃないんですかね？…」&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;しかし、その静寂は長く続かなかった。ほどなくして、驚きの声や車のクラクションの音が一斉に鳴り響き、暗闇の中で慌てる人々の足音や囁きが聞こえてきた。ドアの向こうのほうから、何か忙しないような声や足音がするのに気づく。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;外を見てみると、歩道では立ち止まった人々が携帯電話のライトを点け、細かく振りながら周囲を照らし始めた。ずっと端の方にみえる交差点では信号の灯りが消えている。少しさきに止まるタクシーは停止したまま、進む方向を見失っているようにもみえる。いつもならなんてことのない淡白な蛍光灯で光る向かいのビルは、真っ暗で形も見えない。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;「ちょっと、外にでてみますか」&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;階段には何人か人が見える。非常灯がついているので階段ははっきりと見える。もっと上のほうで働いている人は気の毒だと思った。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;外に出ると、少しだけスマホのライトをちらつかせてスーツで歩いてる人がみえる。向こう側の同僚をみたとき顔が照らされていたときと同じように、道を見渡す限り目がとまる明かりはすべてスマホを持つ人々だ。そこまで広くない一本道に沿った明かりは、ずーっと先のほうまで続いているのが見て取れる。四角く区切られたこの街が明かりを失ったとき、灯るのはスマホだけなのだろう。普段なら意識もしないビル外は、こんなに遠くまで広がっているのだと気づかなかった。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;電気を待つしかない、そう思ったときはじめて見上げた空に驚いた。小さな光が空を一面に埋め尽くしている。五年以上も前に、雫を初めて東京の空でみたときに見たとき、はるか遠くから降ってくる光を見たのを思い出した。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;しかしその光はよくみると、動いていない。どの光も、その場に止まったままだ。それが雫でなく、本物の恒星による光だと気づいたとき、はっと息を呑んだ。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;「ちょっとこれ、もしかしなくても星…?」&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;「おーーーい！こりゃ大変だな」&lt;br /&gt;
降りてきた同僚の声がする。振り返ってみると、他の光と同じように彼の顔も白く照らされている。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;「…いや、ちょっとこれ見てくれ」&lt;br /&gt;
「お、何かわかったか！？」&lt;br /&gt;
「いや、そうじゃなくて..」&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;空のほうを指さして、スマホで照らされる彼の顔は困った顔をしている、
「え…? うわあ、すごい量の雫だな….!って、、あれ..?」&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;一瞬、静けさが戻ってきた。先までを照らしていた道路を照らす光も消えた。ビルから降りてきた人の声も、周りのざわめきも。皆は顔をあげて空を見ているようだった。降ってくるはずの動く光を探しては、動かず空を埋めつくすその模様からしばらく、目が離せなかった。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/story/droplet_finale.png&quot; class=&quot;mx-auto my-4&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;その時抱いた一抹の不安はどこかへ消えどれくらいの時間が立ったのか、もう思い出せない。思い出せるのは、誰かが叫んだ「雫だ！」と叫んだその感極まった声、そのあとにかすかにながらハッキリと聞こえた気がした、ビルの間で反響した不安から解放される小さな声。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;あれから3年がたった今日も、このぼやっとした4階のデスクに座るとたまに思い出す。変わっているようで、それでも、何も変わっていないのだ。&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>[{&quot;name&quot;=&gt;&quot;Daisuke Miyazaki&quot;}, {&quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;daisuke.miyazaki012@gmail.com&quot;}]</name></author><category term="jp" /><summary type="html">地球温暖化予想2050年シナリオは最悪のケースをたどったため、2047年中旬、国連総本部は迅速かつこれまでにない世界的な協力が必要と声明を表示した。日本はその一環として新しい年号を定め、2050年より年号を改める方針を打ち出し、世界中の共通年号として共有された。</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Workbench</title><link href="https://mdaisuke.net/en/2023/08/21/workbench/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Workbench" /><published>2023-08-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-08-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mdaisuke.net/en/2023/08/21/workbench</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mdaisuke.net/en/2023/08/21/workbench/">&lt;p&gt;Tried DIY! Gifting a Custom-Made Workbench to My Art-Loving Wife&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/builds/front.jpeg&quot; class=&quot;image_in_post_sm&quot; onclick=&quot;openModalImage(this)&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hello, everyone! Last month, I took up the challenge of making a unique workbench that can’t be found in stores, just for my art-enthusiast wife. I’ve written down the entire process for you here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s wonderful to see my wife enjoying her art, but the clutter in our small room—less than 5 tatami mats in size—is an issue. Storage space is insufficient! Also, the posture while sitting and working is not ideal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I thought that a workbench that allows her to enjoy art while standing could solve these problems. And with that, let the DIY begin!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;before-building-ux-design&quot;&gt;Before Building, UX Design&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I decided the height of the tabletop. I happened to have a height-adjustable desk, so we checked what would be comfortable both when standing and sitting. By roughly observing the centerline of the body, we measured a height that seemed appropriate for when standing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/builds/test0.jpeg&quot; class=&quot;image_in_post_sm&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When sitting down, the line of sight tends to lower.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/builds/test1.jpeg&quot; class=&quot;image_in_post_sm&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this height, her face is still looking down and her neck would be in pain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-container_double&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/builds/test2.jpeg&quot; class=&quot;image_in_post_sm&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/builds/test3.jpeg&quot; class=&quot;image_in_post_sm&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this height, it seems to be mostly straight. Even compared to when standing, you can see that it is mostly centered. I found out that a height of around 110 centimeters is good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;design&quot;&gt;Design&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/builds/cad.jpeg&quot; class=&quot;image_in_post_sm&quot; onclick=&quot;openModalImage(this)&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, I used 3D modeling for the design, considering overall balance, center of gravity, and gathering my wife’s feedback. Key points included:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ample-storage&quot;&gt;Ample Storage&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Art often requires more tools than finished works. &lt;br /&gt;
Large storage is essential to avoid clutter.&lt;br /&gt;
Added doors for items that can become messy during work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;showcasing-inspiration&quot;&gt;Showcasing Inspiration&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Books, magazines, cards, and trinkets are items she wants to display.&lt;br /&gt;
We envisioned open storage to keep them in sight.&lt;br /&gt;
Having these items always visible aids in finding inspiration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;space&quot;&gt;Space&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A wider bench is better. I went for one that fills the wall. The tabletop is 50 cm deep, providing just enough space for a laptop.&lt;br /&gt;
The front 20 cm of the tabletop can be folded down, making it more compact when not in use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sourcing-materials&quot;&gt;Sourcing Materials&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, I bought wood based on the design. But here’s where I hit a snag: the wood was not as wide as I had planned. I decided to adjust the scale of the model instead of wasting materials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then, after buying it, came the big problem. How do I transport this wood? I don’t have a car and it won’t fit in a taxi… It’s too hot to carry it outside. I was in trouble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then, I found out that at the hardware store, they offer same-day delivery service that can be used in-store! I was saved by this same-day delivery service. I paid an additional delivery fee and everything was delivered to my house the next day&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;start-building&quot;&gt;Start Building&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the wood arrives, all that’s left is to build. I’ll continue building it just as I imagined. Here’s the progress so far…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/builds/inProgress.jpeg&quot; class=&quot;image_in_post_sm&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the door did not turn out to be the size or model I had imagined, I had to retrofit it. I went back to the home center, Konan, for shopping, but it was too hot to carry the huge door on our bicycles. It would have been foolish to pay for shipping again…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At that moment, we found out that Konan offers a free rental of a light truck. It was the first time I learned that I could drive it with a regular license and a handle. Thanks to that, I was able to transport it smoothly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-container_double&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/builds/miniTruck.jpeg&quot; class=&quot;image_in_post_sm&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/builds/miniTruck2.jpeg&quot; class=&quot;image_in_post_sm&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started building again. When I attached the door, I had more trouble than I expected with attaching the hinges. I referred to &lt;a href=&quot;https://magazine.cainz.com/article/81662&quot;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; for help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the finishing touch, I applied a coat of varnish. I made sure to ventilate the room properly even in the hot weather. I wore double masks in the room where there is no air conditioner in the room during the summer….&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/builds/hotMan.jpeg&quot; class=&quot;image_in_post_sm&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For finishing, I need measures against falling. It’s a big thing, so it’s essential. I planned to strengthen the legs in the model, but it was too much work to process… After thinking about it, I found this one piece at the home center and it solved the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/builds/legs.jpeg&quot; class=&quot;image_in_post_sm&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I added a back panel to eliminate lateral shaking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/builds/seita.jpeg&quot; class=&quot;image_in_post_sm&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;completion&quot;&gt;Completion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, it’s done!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-container_triple&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/builds/front.jpeg&quot; class=&quot;image_in_post_sm&quot; onclick=&quot;openModalImage(this)&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/builds/front2.jpeg&quot; class=&quot;image_in_post_sm&quot; onclick=&quot;openModalImage(this)&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/builds/front3.jpeg&quot; class=&quot;image_in_post_sm&quot; onclick=&quot;openModalImage(this)&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The foldable tabletop measures 180cm x 50cm, providing ample space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-container_double&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/builds/tableWidth.jpeg&quot; class=&quot;image_in_post_sm&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/builds/faceToCamera.jpeg&quot; class=&quot;image_in_post_sm&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The posture when standing is almost identical to our measurements, promising a comfortable art-making experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-container_double&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/builds/positionCheck.jpeg&quot; class=&quot;image_in_post_sm&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/builds/test3.jpeg&quot; class=&quot;image_in_post_sm&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tabletop also doubles as a door, hiding cables and providing a cleaner look.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- insert image from builds.yml --&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-container_triple&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/builds/foldedTableTop.jpeg&quot; class=&quot;image_in_post_sm&quot; onclick=&quot;openModalImage(this)&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/builds/mount.jpeg&quot; class=&quot;image_in_post_sm&quot; onclick=&quot;openModalImage(this)&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/builds/codes.jpeg&quot; class=&quot;image_in_post_sm&quot; onclick=&quot;openModalImage(this)&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what do you think? Why not use the resources and services around you to DIY something special as a gift?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy Building!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script src=&quot;/assets/js/popup_build.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;myModal&quot; class=&quot;modal&quot;&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;close&quot;&gt;&amp;times;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img class=&quot;modal-content&quot; id=&quot;img01&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;div id=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>[{&quot;name&quot;=&gt;&quot;Daisuke Miyazaki&quot;}, {&quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;daisuke.miyazaki012@gmail.com&quot;}]</name></author><category term="en" /><summary type="html">Tried DIY! Gifting a Custom-Made Workbench to My Art-Loving Wife</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="jp"><title type="html">ワークベンチ</title><link href="https://mdaisuke.net/jp/2023/08/21/%E3%83%99%E3%83%B3%E3%83%81/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ワークベンチ" /><published>2023-08-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-08-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mdaisuke.net/jp/2023/08/21/%E3%83%99%E3%83%B3%E3%83%81</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mdaisuke.net/jp/2023/08/21/%E3%83%99%E3%83%B3%E3%83%81/">&lt;div id=&quot;hihi&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DIYやってみた！アート愛好者の妻へ特製ワークベンチをプレゼント。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/builds/front.jpeg&quot; class=&quot;mx-auto my-4&quot; onclick=&quot;openModalImage(this)&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;こんにちは、皆さん！先月頭、アート愛好者の妻のために、どこにも売っていない特別なワークベンチを作る挑戦をしてみました。こちらにその一部始終を書き下ろしてみました。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;妻がアートを楽しんでいる様子を見るのは素晴らしいこと。でも5畳もないお部屋で散らかり具合…収納が足りない！そして、どうしても座って書いていると姿勢が…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;そこで立ったままアートを楽しむことができるワークベンチがあれば、こんな悩みも解消されるんじゃないかと。そう思って作りはじめてみました。それでは、DIYの開始です！&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;作る前のuxデザイン&quot;&gt;作る前のUXデザイン&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;まず、天板の高さを決めます。たまたま昇降式デスクを使っていたので、立った様子や座った様子を確認。なんとなく体の中心線を見てみて、立ったときに近いような高さを測りました。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/builds/test0.jpeg&quot; class=&quot;mx-auto my-4&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;座っている状態だとどうしても目線が下がってしまいます。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/builds/test1.jpeg&quot; class=&quot;mx-auto my-4&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;この高さだと、まだ顔が下を向いていて首が疲れてしまいそう。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-container_double&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/builds/test2.jpeg&quot; class=&quot;mx-auto my-4&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/builds/test3.jpeg&quot; class=&quot;mx-auto my-4&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;この高さなら、全体的にまっすぐになっていて良さそう。
立った時と比較しても、大体同じくらい中心線になっているのがわかります。こちらで高さは110センチくらいが良さそうだとわかりました。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;uiデザイン&quot;&gt;UIデザイン&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/builds/cad.jpeg&quot; class=&quot;mx-auto my-4&quot; onclick=&quot;openModalImage(this)&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;次に3Dモデリングで設計します。全体のバランスや重心の計算、イメージのすり合わせなどを妻のフィードバックを得ながら作っていきます。こだわった点は…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;大きな収納&quot;&gt;大きな収納&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;⁃ アートも作品よりも道具のほうが数が多くなる。十分な収納がないと散らかってしまうので、大容量が必要&lt;br /&gt;
⁃ ツールや作業中のものなどはごちゃるので扉を取り付け。&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;インスピレーションを綺麗に魅せる&quot;&gt;インスピレーションを綺麗に魅せる&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;⁃ 寄せ集めた書籍や雑誌、旅先で見つけたカードなどは常に見えるように飾っておきたいもの。扉が付く本棚では中身が見えないこともあるので、なるべく見せる収納をイメージ。&lt;br /&gt;
⁃ カードや小物なども、常に見えるように展示することでインスピレーションを得やすくなる。&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;スペース&quot;&gt;スペース&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;⁃ 幅があったほうが良いので壁いっぱいに広がる大きさに。天板は壁いっぱいの横幅 * ノートPCを広げて余裕があるように50cmに。部屋の大きさが限られているので、天板の手前20センチは折りたためるように。&lt;br /&gt;
⁃ 折り畳んだ際には最上段の扉になるように設計。ごちゃってしまうケーブル類はこの段にしまえるように。&lt;br /&gt;
⁃ 再下段にはお掃除ロボットが入ってこれるだけの高さを用意。&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;資材の調達&quot;&gt;資材の調達&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;次に設計図をもとに木材を購入します。近くのホームセンターへ。ここでちょっとしたトラブルが…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;計画した幅よりも、実際の木材の幅が狭かったんです。大きいものを切ってもらうと端材が出てしまって勿体無い。。困った挙句、ではこの最大幅を活かして作って仕舞えば良いや！と思いきって決断。モデルで組んだものを、比率を保ったまま少し少し小さくするイメージでした。
…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;そして買ったはいいものの、その後の大問題。この木材、どうやって運ぶ？車は持っていないしタクシーにも入らない、、、真夏でとてもじゃないけれど外では運べない。困った。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;思いきやここでなんとコーナンでは、当日配達サービスが店内で利用できるとのこと！この当日配送サービスに助けられました。配送料を追加で支払い、翌日にはすべてお家へ届くとのことで活用。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;作成開始&quot;&gt;作成開始&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;木材が届いたら、あとは作るのみ。イメージ通りに作っていきます。こちら途中経過…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/builds/inProgress.jpeg&quot; class=&quot;mx-auto my-4&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;扉は寸法もモデルで見ていた通りにならなかったので後付けにしました。買い出しに再度ホームセンターのコーナンへ、暑いので自転車でむかったものの巨大すぎるドアをどうも運べず。再度配送料を払うのもバカバカしい。。。
そんなときなんと、コーナンでは軽トラを無料で借りれることが判明。ハンドルつき、普通免許で運転できることも初めて知りました。おかげ様でスムーズに運ぶことができました。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-container_double&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/builds/miniTruck.jpeg&quot; class=&quot;mx-auto my-4&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/builds/miniTruck2.jpeg&quot; class=&quot;mx-auto my-4&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;再度作成開始。扉をつけるとき、蝶番をつけるのに思ったよりも苦戦しました、、&lt;a href=&quot;https://magazine.cainz.com/article/81662&quot;&gt;こちら&lt;/a&gt;を参照にしました。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;仕上げにはニス塗りもしっかりと。あっつい部屋でもしっかりと換気をしつつ。真夏のクーラーの効かない部屋で二重マスク。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/builds/hotMan.jpeg&quot; class=&quot;mx-auto my-4&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;仕上げには転倒対策。大きなものなのでこちらも必須です。モデルでは足を強固にする予定だったけれど加工が手間で面倒くさい。。。色々考えてみた結果、ホームセンターで見つけたこいつ一枚で解決。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/builds/legs.jpeg&quot; class=&quot;mx-auto my-4&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;また、横揺れもしたので背板をつけることで解消しました。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/builds/seita.jpeg&quot; class=&quot;mx-auto my-4&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;完成&quot;&gt;完成&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;そしてついに完成！&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-container_triple&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/builds/front.jpeg&quot; class=&quot;mx-auto my-4&quot; onclick=&quot;openModalImage(this)&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/builds/front2.jpeg&quot; class=&quot;mx-auto my-4&quot; onclick=&quot;openModalImage(this)&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/builds/front3.jpeg&quot; class=&quot;mx-auto my-4&quot; onclick=&quot;openModalImage(this)&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;折りたたみ式の天板も180cm * 50cmと十分な広さがあります。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-container_double&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/builds/tableWidth.jpeg&quot; class=&quot;mx-auto my-4&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/builds/faceToCamera.jpeg&quot; class=&quot;mx-auto my-4&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;立った時の姿勢も、測ったときの姿勢とほぼ一致しています。これで快適にアートに取り組めるはず！&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-container_double&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/builds/positionCheck.jpeg&quot; class=&quot;mx-auto my-4&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/builds/test3.jpeg&quot; class=&quot;mx-auto my-4&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;天板が扉の役割も兼用し、コードなども隠して見た目もすっきりするように。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- insert image from builds.yml --&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-container_triple&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/builds/foldedTableTop.jpeg&quot; class=&quot;mx-auto my-4&quot; onclick=&quot;openModalImage(this)&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/builds/mount.jpeg&quot; class=&quot;mx-auto my-4&quot; onclick=&quot;openModalImage(this)&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/daisukemiyazaki_website/builds/codes.jpeg&quot; class=&quot;mx-auto my-4&quot; onclick=&quot;openModalImage(this)&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;いかがでしょうか？皆さんも、身近なものやサービスを利用しながら、特別なものをDIYで作って贈ってみてはみてはいかがでしょうか？&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy Building!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script src=&quot;/assets/js/popup_build.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;myModal&quot; class=&quot;modal&quot;&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;close&quot;&gt;&amp;times;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img class=&quot;modal-content&quot; id=&quot;img01&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;div id=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>[{&quot;name&quot;=&gt;&quot;Daisuke Miyazaki&quot;}, {&quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;daisuke.miyazaki012@gmail.com&quot;}]</name></author><category term="jp" /><summary type="html">DIY！アート愛好者の妻へ特製ワークベンチをプレゼント。どこにも売っていない特別なワークベンチを作る挑戦をしてみました。その一部始終を書き下ろしてみました。</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Going-Meta-In-The-MetaVerse</title><link href="https://mdaisuke.net/en/2022/12/09/Going-Meta-In-The-MetaVerse/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Going-Meta-In-The-MetaVerse" /><published>2022-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mdaisuke.net/en/2022/12/09/Going-Meta-In-The-MetaVerse</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mdaisuke.net/en/2022/12/09/Going-Meta-In-The-MetaVerse/">&lt;style&gt;
  #profile {
    right: 0;
    float: right;
    width: 30%;
    height: 30%;
    border-radius: 50%;
    border: 2px solid #fff;
    box-shadow: 0 0 10px rgba(0, 0, 0, 0.5);
    position: relative;
  }
  #profile:hover {
    border: 2px solid #000;
  }
  .profile__wrapper {
    height: 30%;
    position: relative;
    padding-left: 20px;
    margin: 0 auto;
  }
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;profile__wrapper&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img id=&quot;profile&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/me.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hello world!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I saw a new step in the revolution so I’m writing it down. &lt;a href=&quot;https://prisma-ai.com/lensa&quot;&gt;I got a new face&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re what you are seen is the same perspective in the computational world and in the non-computational world. However, the difference is that in the former world we can go beyond of our appearance that is tied to the non-computational world. In reality, ML and traditional computation are merged with the non-computational world, and the definition of “What am I in this world? keeps changing. Rethinking how to be in this world, it is surely more of the state of fusion than ever. The data used to create the new face is the mugshots of the non-computational world, but let us not forget that it was predominantly the gift of the visual arts of collective wisdom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Visual information is an important part of life, and I felt that this face fits well into my way of being. It is the flip side of the fact that even in the computational world, the individual from non-computational world is still connected. But what’s surprising is that the creation of the face took &lt;a href=&quot;https://prisma-ai.com/lensa&quot;&gt;only 20 minutes and a few dollars&lt;/a&gt;. The level of fitness in this ever-changing dynamic of reality and its accessibility is truly astonishing and unprecedented, and today is a day that marked a new step in &lt;a href=&quot;https://mdaisuke.net/en/2020/01/20/%E3%82%B5%E3%82%A4%E3%83%88%E5%A7%8B%E5%8B%95/&quot;&gt;the revolution&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>[{&quot;name&quot;=&gt;&quot;Daisuke Miyazaki&quot;}, {&quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;daisuke.miyazaki012@gmail.com&quot;}]</name></author><category term="en" /><summary type="html">I saw a new step in the revolution so I&apos;m writing it down. I got a new face.</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="jp"><title type="html">新しい一歩</title><link href="https://mdaisuke.net/jp/2022/12/09/%E6%96%B0%E3%81%97%E3%81%84%E4%B8%80%E6%AD%A9/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="新しい一歩" /><published>2022-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mdaisuke.net/jp/2022/12/09/%E6%96%B0%E3%81%97%E3%81%84%E4%B8%80%E6%AD%A9</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mdaisuke.net/jp/2022/12/09/%E6%96%B0%E3%81%97%E3%81%84%E4%B8%80%E6%AD%A9/">&lt;style&gt;
  #profile {
    right: 0;
    float: right;
    width: 30%;
    height: 30%;
    border-radius: 50%;
    border: 2px solid #fff;
    box-shadow: 0 0 10px rgba(0, 0, 0, 0.5);
    position: relative;
  }
  #profile:hover {
    border: 2px solid #000;
  }
  .profile__wrapper {
    height: 30%;
    position: relative;
    padding-left: 20px;
    margin: 0 auto;
  }
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;profile__wrapper&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img id=&quot;profile&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/me.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hello world!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;革命の新しい一歩を見たので、書き留めておく。&lt;a href=&quot;https://prisma-ai.com/lensa&quot;&gt;新しい顔ができた&lt;/a&gt;のだ。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;計算機上世界の自己は周りから見られるものである、という観点は非計算機世界でも同じことが言える。しかし前者の世界では容姿を大きく創造することができる点が異なる。どのみちこの世界ではMLや計算機は非計算機世界と融合しており、「この世界で自分とは何か？」と在り方を見つめ直しても、それも融合状態にあることに変わりはない。新しい顔を創るのに使用したデータは非計算機世界の顔写真であるが、支配的だったのは集団叡智による視覚的芸術の賜物であったことを忘れないようにしたい。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;視覚的情報とは生物にとって生活の重要な一部である中で、この顔はそんな自分の在り方にうまくハマったと感じた。拡張世界においても個が紐づいていることの裏返しでもあるが、顔の創造にかかったのは&lt;a href=&quot;https://prisma-ai.com/lensa&quot;&gt;僅か20分と数百円&lt;/a&gt;。&lt;a href=&quot;https://mdaisuke.net/jp/2020/01/20/%E3%82%B5%E3%82%A4%E3%83%88%E5%A7%8B%E5%8B%95/&quot;&gt;高度に大衆化した革命&lt;/a&gt;の新しい一歩を記録した日と言えるだろう。&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>[{&quot;name&quot;=&gt;&quot;Daisuke Miyazaki&quot;}, {&quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;daisuke.miyazaki012@gmail.com&quot;}]</name></author><category term="jp" /><summary type="html">革命の新しい一歩を見たので、書き留めておく。新しい顔ができたのだ。計算機上世界の自己は周りから見られるものである。非計算機世界でも同じことが言える。</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="jp"><title type="html">緑化のススメ</title><link href="https://mdaisuke.net/jp/2022/08/08/%E7%B7%91%E5%8C%96%E3%81%AE%E3%82%B9%E3%82%B9%E3%83%A1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="緑化のススメ" /><published>2022-08-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-08-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mdaisuke.net/jp/2022/08/08/%E7%B7%91%E5%8C%96%E3%81%AE%E3%82%B9%E3%82%B9%E3%83%A1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mdaisuke.net/jp/2022/08/08/%E7%B7%91%E5%8C%96%E3%81%AE%E3%82%B9%E3%82%B9%E3%83%A1/">&lt;!-- an image of vegetables from the desk --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/vegetable.JPG&quot; class=&quot;image_in_post&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;width:80%; margin:0 auto; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;書斎から&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;どうしてこれを書くのか&quot;&gt;どうしてこれを書くのか&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2020 年の末から、ベランダ園芸に身が入っている。「もう定年？」なんてジョークを言われたこともあるくらいである。はじめたきっかけは 2 つある。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;まず、緑が好きだから。たとえば緑豊かなレストランを通り過ぎるときや、野菜が並ぶホームセンターではどこか魅力を感じて、いつのまにか足を止めてしまう。ハイキングなどで森の中を歩くときも気持ちはいいもので、どこか気持ちが惹かれるのである。そこで手元で始めてみることにした、というわけである。&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;かなり先の未来にこんなものがあったらいいな、と思いついたアイデアによるものである。その未来とは、多くの車が完全自立運転機能を搭載し実用化されたときのことを指す。一見まるで緑とは関係ないように思えるかもしれない。しかしそんな未来を想像すると、ある 1 つ決定的に変わると思われるものがある。&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;それは、今ある駐車場のスペースは使われなくなることだ。なぜなら現在の車のうち、90%の時間は停車しているから。もし、停車しなくても他に使い道があれば(たとえば、ずっと車を回してタクシーとして使用するなど)、オーナーにとっても運転させ続けるほうが経済的に理にかなっているに違いない。そうするともちろん駐車場は使われなくなるので、余った土地を何かに有効活用したくなる。&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;ではどのように使うのか？ここに、緑化に一票を入れたいという結論である。緑が増えた東京の街はもっと帰ってきたくなる都市になると思う。でも漠然と指す緑とは森林のような樹木を指すのか、庭園のようなものを指すのか、それとも農業用の畑を指すのか？活用の仕方もさまざまで、鑑賞するのか、それとも食用とするのか？まずは一緒に暮らすことで見えてくるのではないか、と考えた。&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;私は都心に住んでいるからこそ、どんな緑が欲しくなるのかというのは、自分で作って一緒に暮らすことによって初めて明らかになるものだと思う。所感をまとめ上げることで、他の人からも違う考えをもってもらったり、どんな緑と暮らしたくなるのかを想像する機会になってもらえればと思うのである。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1-年間くらい一緒に暮らしてみて気づいたこと&quot;&gt;1 年間くらい一緒に暮らしてみて気づいたこと&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;というわけで何かと園芸を始めたのが去年の夏過ぎ、しばらく時間が経ったので、２つのきっかけを元に振り返りをしてみたい。1 つ目のきっかけ、ただ好きなのはそもそもどうしてなのか？いくつかそれらしい答えが見つかったので書き留めてみる。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;まず一緒に暮らしてみて大きく感じたこと、それは緑が目にもたらす優しい景色が家をさらに家らしくしてくれることであった。&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;暑い夏、大きな樹木の木陰では涼をとれるし、喧騒の中に静けさをもたらしてくれる。窓越しに慣れ親しんだ緑にはどこか、戻ってきたくなるような気持ちを覚えるのだった。僕の部屋は西向きなので、昼過ぎになると日が差し込んでは影を作りだし、風に靡く様子もまた落ち着く。こうして緑は、自宅をより居心地の良いところにしてくれることに大きく役立っている。&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;仕事柄よく在宅勤務をするようになり、自宅で過ごす時間もかなり増えている。カフェで仕事をしようと外に出向いてみても、結局は一番居心地が良いところを求めて家に戻ってくることが多い。また仕事でなくても、緑豊かなカフェに行くと自然と好感が湧くのも一層うなづけるし、モダンで大きな会社では緑が身近な場所にあることにも納得がいくのであった。&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;家にもたらしてくれる刺激の 1 つとしても、緑は大きな役に立っている。猫や犬と一緒に暮らすとわかるように、植物の習性も垣間見ることができるようになった。春先に公園に出向くと桜が満開になっていたり、秋の真っ只中に紅葉に色づいてく緑に気づくことに近しいと思う。&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;一瞬止まっているように見える植物は、ただ人の時間軸で暮らしていない。毎日朝に水をあげるたびに、芽を出したり、色が変わったり、場所によって葉の先端が枯れ始めていたりする。いつのまにか大きくなって背を抜かしたり、茎に触れただけではっきりとわかるトマトや、鼻をくすぐるラベンダーやタイムの香り。五感に訴えるような体験は、デジタルなエンターテイメントに慣れた僕にとって新鮮だと感じる。&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;また育て方にもよるが、新鮮な野菜を調達しては食べることしか味わえない体験でもある。ネギ、オレガノ、タイム、パセリ、ローズマリーといった香草系は虫もつかずよく育つ。また朝ごはんに欲しい、ちょっとした味噌汁の具材としても使えたりして、いちいち買い足さなくてもよくなる。必要な分だけを収穫して食べることができ、冷蔵庫のスペースも節約できる。&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;さらにコンポスト用の苗を 1 つ作り、普段の食事で出た茶葉やコーヒーの殻やバナナの皮、野菜の皮などのゴミを土に住むシマミミズへ与えることで、肥沃な土に繋がる。普段はゴミとして捨てているものが、新しい命の始まりに回っている様子を見ることは楽しいものである。&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;最後に、僕 1 人でなく他の人からの意見ももらって気づいたことがあるので書き留めておく。僕はシェアハウスに住んでいて、いろんな仕事を持つ人と一緒に暮らしている。そのため皆の共通の話題というのは仕事の外にあり、多くの場合はイベントだったりこの地域の話だったり、食事だったりすることが多い。そんな中で園芸の話をしたり庭を見せたりすると、肯定的な意見を貰うことが多いのである。つまり職種の垣根を超えて、人は好感を覚えるんだなと肌感で思った。&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;難しさ&quot;&gt;難しさ&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;また一緒に暮らすことによって、気づいた難しさがあるのも事実であるから、これも一緒に書き留めておく。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;以前、緑と本格的に住む前には「植物は苗に移して、あとは水をやるだけ」と思っていた。でも一緒に住んでみることでそれだけに収まらない難しさがあることに気づいたのでまとめてみる。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;日当たり&lt;/strong&gt;
結局ほとんどの野菜は、室内の日当たりでは足りず直射日光が半日以上当たる環境にいる必要がある。&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;十分な水やり&lt;/strong&gt;
なんだかんだ毎日のように水をやるのは面倒になってしまうし、旅行などで長く家を外す時には友人に頼んだりする必要がある。体験としては水やりもいいけれど、保持には水やりの自動化を検討する必要があると思う。&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;苗の大きさ選び&lt;/strong&gt;
植物の大きさは苗の大きさによって決まる。高く成長することには強風が吹いたときに風を受け止める表面積が増加し、その結果倒されてしまうリスクが発生らしい。そのため、十分に大きい地面には相応の広さの根を張ってこれに備えるが、苗の大きさが頭打ちしているとその分高さも頭打ちする。結果、収穫量などに直結する。
その反面で、ベランダで育てる苗の大きさにも限界があるし、移動させたり管理することが難しくなる。収穫量とメンテナンス、スペースの塩梅は探り探りである。&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;収穫の絶対量&lt;/strong&gt;
普段の食生活を支えるほどの野菜の収穫量には到底届かないことは、始めてから 3 か月も経てば明らかなことだった。だからこそ農家さんの作った農作物が、スーパーに行けば数百円で手に入る事実には、あらためて感謝を覚えるのであった。&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;苗の中での多様性&lt;/strong&gt;
例えばトマトとバジルは、お互いに過不足となる栄養素が補完関係にあるらしい。マメ科の植物は「根粒」という特殊な器官によって植物の五大栄養素のうち１つである窒素を、空気中から地下に固定する。キク科の植物は、たとえばセリ科に寄りやすい虫を退ける特性がある。異なる科目の植物を混植し、多様性を保つことで相互の成長を促進できる(ローズマリーなど、中には混植を避けた方がよい苗も存在するが)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;虫対策&lt;/strong&gt;
アブラムシは大量に発生する。あっという間に増殖し植物を埋め尽くしては水分を取り除いてしまい、結果的に植物は枯れてしまう。農薬を使うか、地道にガムテープなどをつかってとっていくか。結果、飛ばないナミテントウという天敵生体を使う方法を実行した。結果アブラムシを駆除できた反面、高価であったり、一部ネットが必要になったりして場所の制約をうけてしまう。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;2-つめの観点について&quot;&gt;2 つめの観点について&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;これまでの話から、緑と住むことのどんな側面に喜びや和みを覚えるのかがよりはっきりとしたし、またどんな課題が残るのかも明確になった。これらはこのような近未来のサービス実用化の考察にむけて、良い開始点になったと思う。これからも緑と暮らし続けることで視座を深め、夢のようなサービスに取り組むきっかけになればいいなあと思うのであった。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;まとめ&quot;&gt;まとめ&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;この投稿を読んで、少しでもベランダで菜園を始めてみようという気持ちに傾いてくれたら幸いである。まだまだ僕も初心者であるし、これからも知見を共有していきたいと思う。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;東京はとても好きだけれど、今よりも緑が増えたこのまちはもっと良い街になると思う。自動運転が進んだ世の中で空いたスペースに緑が増え、また電動化が進むことで荒れ狂う内燃機関の音も少なくなり、より閑静化するであろう。東京をどんな街にしたいか？という質問はいわば真っ白のカンヴァスを手にするようなもの。緑はそのカンヴァスに、人の心の拠り所になるような色を与えてくれるに違いない。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;参考文献: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.jp/gp/product/B07D4DD9K9/ref=ppx_yo_dt_b_search_asin_title?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;psc=1&quot;&gt;ベランダ菜園&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kinokuniya.co.jp/f/dsg-08-EK-0290191&quot;&gt;植物は＜知性＞をもっている ２０の感覚で思考する生命システム&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.jp/dp/B07K13W24C/ref=dp-kindle-redirect?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;btkr=1&quot;&gt;樹木たちの知られざる生活 森林管理官が聴いた森の声 (ハヤカワ文庫 NF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>[{&quot;name&quot;=&gt;&quot;Daisuke Miyazaki&quot;}, {&quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;daisuke.miyazaki012@gmail.com&quot;}]</name></author><category term="jp" /><summary type="html">2020 年の末から、ベランダ園芸に身が入っている。「もう定年？」なんてジョークを言われたこともあるくらいである。はじめたきっかけは2つある。</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="jp"><title type="html">Gapyear</title><link href="https://mdaisuke.net/jp/2022/05/06/%E3%82%AE%E3%83%A3%E3%83%83%E3%83%97%E3%82%A4%E3%83%A4%E3%83%BC/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gapyear" /><published>2022-05-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-05-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mdaisuke.net/jp/2022/05/06/%E3%82%AE%E3%83%A3%E3%83%83%E3%83%97%E3%82%A4%E3%83%A4%E3%83%BC</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mdaisuke.net/jp/2022/05/06/%E3%82%AE%E3%83%A3%E3%83%83%E3%83%97%E3%82%A4%E3%83%A4%E3%83%BC/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;どうしてこれを書くのか&quot;&gt;どうしてこれを書くのか&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;まず何よりも、私が初心に戻って振り返るため。また、当時(そしてきっと今も)前例が日本では少なかったし、当時ギャップイヤーを選択した人は周りに 1 人もいなかったため、キャリアの相談をすることできませんでした。そのためこの記事が、誰かの参考になればと思った次第です。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;今は 2022 年 5 月。たった 4 年で時代は変わってしまったと肌感で思います。当時 2018 年、スーツを着て出社することが当たり前の時代だったけれど、今は(できる人は)在宅勤務が当たり前の時代。誰も話してなかったような脱炭素の話は、昨今では目新しい話ではなくなりました。例えば産業界では、米電気自動車のテスラ社はモデル 3 の量産地獄や空売り被害を受け数字的にも厳しかったけれど、今となってはトヨタの時価総額を超えるほどの会社へ成長しました。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;当時私は物理の学位を取得したものの、今は web 開発を行なって生計を立てています。現職が少しずつ板につき、数年前と比べて見える景色も随分と変わりました。当時抱いていた疑問とそれに対する答えも、ある程度まとまったのでここに書き留めます。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;そもそもギャップイヤーとは何か&quot;&gt;そもそもギャップイヤーとは何か&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;学校を卒業してから 1 年間、自分の人生と向き合う時間をとることを指します。欧米では gap year と言葉は浸透しており、主に高校卒業あるいは大学卒業後に時間をとり、旅行をする人が多いです。例えば&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rR0v6UKbQPc&quot;&gt;こちら&lt;/a&gt;。特に政府などが決めているものではないのでどんな方法でも良いのが特徴です。行政上の立場はフリーターとなります。ざっと振り返ってみて、私にとっては将来にむけてスキルを構築する、という方針が主軸にあったと思います。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;当時のモチベーション&quot;&gt;当時のモチベーション&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;どうしてこの選択をしたのか、当時のモチベーションを箇条書きにしてみます。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;立ち止まって考えてごらん？&lt;/strong&gt;学校を卒業するまで、ずっと教育を受けることに専念します。それから働き始めてからの一生は定年を 60 歳とすると 40 年弱、そして老後。その間一度たりとして、働くことを世間から要求されても、「立ち止まって考えてみてごらん？」ということは誰からも言われません。人生のステージって 3 つしか用意されてないんでしょうか？&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;見極めてから仕事を探すべきでは？&lt;/strong&gt;日本の新卒採用では、大学の 4 年生のうち最も重要である最後の年に就職活動を行います。卒業するとすぐに新卒として、内定をもらった会社に入社します。特徴的なのは、会社がある程度候補者のポテンシャルを見て、社員を育ててくれることです。極端な話、例えば文学を勉強してから社会人になって IT エンジニアをやることだってできるのです。これは素晴らしい制度であり、「大学や大学院の専門が職務に必要となる」といった欧米では珍しい制度です。あまりしかしそもそも理系の場合は、就職活動をするタイミングが卒業論文を書くタイミングとぶつかります。3 年生までに積み上げてきた基礎的な学問をもってして、専門家の社会的な役割である「研究成果を出す」一番初めのトライアルに 100%時間を捧げられないことになります。&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;高校生を卒業するタイミングで専門家として進みたい道が決まっているなら話は別ですが、そもそも学科で学んでいること自体が自分の興味と外れていく可能性だって十分にあり得えます。&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;さらに大学に行くには理系の私立大学の場合、4 年間で 600 万円ほどかかります。そんな中で、学業をしながらも就職活動をするというのは教育というサービスを「支払って受けている」理に適っていないのではないでしょうか？&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;まとめ直すと、こうなります。つまり大学の 4 年間は学業に専念し、卒業してから本当にその道が自分にあっていたかを見つめ直し、それから就職活動をすべきではないでしょうか。&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;専門分野外で、勉強したいことや成果物として形に残したいものがあったから。&lt;/strong&gt; 2 の見極るにあたって、まとまった時間があるからこそできるところだと思います。私の場合は例として、本の上梓やプログラミングの勉強、気候変動問題への取り組みなど&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ギャップイヤー終了時に経済的に独立していること。&lt;/strong&gt;尊敬する母親からの教えです。やりたいことをやるなら、親の脛をかじらずに自立してから。&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;もちろんこれらは成功する保証はなかったけれども、以上の質問に答えてみたかったのです。両親にも説得をし、大学を卒業したら家から出て行け、というポリシーでしたが 1 年だけ家に留まれることに。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ではギャップイヤーが終わり社会人として丸 3 年間働いた今から見て、答え合わせをしてみましょう。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;答え合わせ&quot;&gt;答え合わせ&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-q-立ち止まってごらん&quot;&gt;1. Q. 立ち止まってごらん？&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A. 立ち止まって正解でした。私の場合この 1 年は、2 の「仕事の見極め」につながるように、うまく社会人生活を過ごせるような準備期間としての色が強かったです。「うまく社会人生活」一つ定義するだけで千差万別ですが、給与、私生活とのバランス、仕事内容、会社内の文化にハマるか否か、性格との一致、俯瞰してみた時の仕事の社会的な役割、名声、キャリアの伸びしろ、市場での需要など、図る物差しには順不同で枚挙にいとまがありません。特にミレニアル世代に生まれたからなのか、「俯瞰してみた時の社会的な役割」や「世界へのインパクト」などといった大義名分に駆られやすい私にとって、立ち止まって向き合う時間があったからこそ、それ以外で自分に合うものさしを発見できたのだと思います。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;その後 3 年間働いたことで得られることもたくさんありました。ギャップイヤーの経験があったからこそ、いずれまとまった時間を取ったときにもまた勝手がわかると思います。「学生」「社会人」「老後」に限らず選択があることは間違いないと自負できます。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2q-見極めてから仕事を探すべきでは&quot;&gt;2.Q. 見極めてから仕事を探すべきでは？&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A. 半分正解で半分間違っていました。
正しかったのは物理学を生かしたキャリアを選択するのではなく、「エンジニアリング」をキャリアとして選択したことです。これは研究職などの理論物理学から一般的に進んだ人キャリアとは異なります。(理由は範囲外になるので、本記事では割愛します)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;間違っていたのは、エンジニアリングという仕事を選択肢として、ある目標を叶えようとした期待値の設定でした。これは「ある問題を解決するため」に「xx をやる」という考え方によります。現実的には思っていた通りには行かなかなかったのです。具体的に「気候変動問題を解決する」ために「エンジニアとして電気自動車を作る」でしたが、職についたものの 1 年半で転職することとなりました。目指したかった方向性と仕事でこなす日々の TODO が乖離していたことが原因でした。読み飛ばしてもらっても構いません。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;電動化を推し進めるべく電気自動車の開発に携わりたかったものの、当時派遣の立場だったのが理由なのか、仕事に就くには求められるのは数年をこなした技術者で、ジュニアのポジションにチャンスはありませんでした。あったのは体制が整った内燃機関関連の仕事のみでした。つまり自社製品の開発となってもリソースとして最先端を割きたい分、新卒にはチャンスは回ってこないのでしょうか。経験がなければ、若い闘志を燃やせる、ほどの環境が揃っていなかったとも言えます。2. 石油や石炭、天然ガスを回すインフラ（ガソリンスタンドやロジスティックス、企業間の付き合い）、内燃機関輸送物（車、トラックなど）を作る工場や雇用（とくに技術職）によって何十億以上という規模で経済が循環していることが理由なのかもしれません。3. 新人につくメンターなどを整えながら教育していく体制も、同じように整っていないのかもしれません。4. 工場勤務や R＆D センターは郊外に位置することが多く、勤務地に居住区が縛られることによって都会での生活を犠牲にせざるを得ません。一部の自動車会社は都内に拠点もありますが、エンジニアリングに携わるとなると郊外に飛ぶ可能性が高いです。多様な人材を採用したい企業にとっては都心部にオフィスを構えたり、在宅ワークなどを徹底して誘致すべきだと思います。気候変動についてもっと柔軟に考えるきっかけになりましたが、それ以降の話は別記事で扱います。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;この方向性で仕事を通してかかわっていくならば、大学(そしておそらく大学院などを修了して)でまたモーターやバッテリー工学を専門に勉強しなおしたりする必要があったのかもしれません。しかし経済的独立という観点と当たってしまったので断念せざるを得ませんでした。しかし方向性は違えど、現職も「エンジニア」としてのキャリアがあるのは、この時の決断があったからだと思います。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-専門分野外で勉強したいことや成果物として形に残したいものがあったから&quot;&gt;3. 専門分野外で、勉強したいことや成果物として形に残したいものがあったから&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;まず物理を学修した時には、この道の専門家としての仕事には関心がない、と気づいていました。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;学生時代は物理の他に英語の勉強に夢中になっており、海外から来た人との異文化交流などの時間も徐々に増え、卒業する頃にはいつの間にか英語が生活の中に溶け込んでいました。(そして今年、アメリカ人の女性と結婚してしまったまでです)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;「日本人は英語が話せない」とよく言われる中で、上達するにつれて、ひとりでも多くの人が英語が話せるようにできることはないかと少しずつ考えるようになりました。「どうして英語が話せるの？」とか「英語を教えてほしい」と聞かれることが多くなったからです。こんな本があるからぜひ読んでみて、と一冊に全てを詰められてたらどうかと大学を卒業する前くらいから考え始めていました。そして 3 月の卒業からまるまる 5 ヶ月後の 8 月下旬までに原稿を書き上げ、このレベルまで至ったイロハを全て詰めた&lt;a href=&quot;https://mdaisuke.net/jp/2018/08/30/%E6%8B%99%E6%9B%B8/&quot;&gt;本を amazon 上で上梓しました&lt;/a&gt;。まだ学校を卒業したばかりでスキルは少なかったので、まずは形にすることが先決しました。(必要だったのは時間と体力のみで、Amazon では出版にお金がかからないため。)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;書いたら売れて経済的に独立できる世界線だと安直に思っていましたが。けれど大間違いで、例えば本は書いてから数を売り切ることもまた苦労すると学びました。もちろん、ギャップイヤー中に行った就職活動では他の人との差別化に大きく関与しましたし、とりあえず形にすることで得られる視座があったのは間違いないですが。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;また、ギャップイヤーがはじまったときから英語を教える前線に立ってみたく塾講師のアルバイトもしてみました。熱意とは別に、実際に続けれるのか、向き不向きなどを試してみたかったからです。振り返ってみれば、アルバイトの中でこの仕事は 1 番自分に合っていて、この道で進み続ける世界線も十分にあったと思います。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;英語とは別ですが、学生 1 年生のときから関心があった気候変動問題にも動きがありました。4 月下旬ごろ、たまたま電気自動車の会社 Tesla の日本法人で営業職インターンのポジションに応募がかかっていたのです。これは舞い降りてきたチャンスだと思って「業種は選ばず仕事さえできれば」と熱意だけで応募しましたが、最後まで辿り着けず落ちてしまいました。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;こうしていくつか挑戦していても、どれも芳しい結果がついてくるわけでもなければ、経済的独立や「うまい社会人生活」を考慮して挑戦し続けられるだけの勢いがあったわけではありませんでした。語学以外にも、結果何かしらスキルがないとやって行けないのだろうと考えました。そこで&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.jp/dp/B07BKVP9QY/ref=dp-kindle-redirect?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;btkr=1&quot;&gt;「独学プログラマー」&lt;/a&gt;という本を手に取ってプログラミングを学び始めつつ、wordpress などでブログを作ってみたりしました(興味関心のあったサステイナブル系のネタを扱ってみたり)。結果、ギャップイヤー後ですがサイトは自分でソースコードを書いて移行し、偶然なのかこれが前職のきっかけになったりしています。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;英語の話や気候変動に対する熱、プログラミングには共通項があまりないですが、1 つだけ言えることがあります。それは将来にむけてスキルを構築する、という方針がギャップイヤーの主軸にあったからこそ、後々の人生まで読めない中で勢いよく、後先考えず思い切って試行錯誤を繰り返すことができたこと。これは学生をやった後にとるギャップイヤーの強みの一つでしょう。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1 つ受けよりですが、スキルを伸ばすにあたって大きく参考になる引用があります。Tesla のオートパイロットチームで有名な Andrej Karpathy さんの言葉です。一部の界隈では有名なエンジニアであり機械学習をアカデミック界のみならず産業界でも強く牽引しています。以下&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/karpathy/status/1325154823856033793?s=20&amp;amp;t=JKgd9wNeGDhcqK6RQyLbJQ&quot;&gt;引用&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;How to become expert at thing:
1 iteratively take on concrete projects and accomplish them depth wise, learning “on demand” (ie don’t learn bottom up breadth wise)
2 teach/summarize everything you learn in your own words
3 only compare yourself to younger you, never to others&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;訳すと以下のようになります。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;物事の専門家になるには
1 具体的なプロジェクトを繰り返し行い「オンデマンド」で学びながら、深さ方向に進める（つまり幅方向にボトムアップで学ばない）。
2 学んだことはすべて自分の言葉で教える／要約する。
3 自分と比較するのは若いうちだけで、決して他人と比較してはならない&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;上で述べた試行錯誤をしている中でメンターがいないので、こういった指針は大きく参考になります。また 3 つのステップまでやってみてから振り返ることで、ある程度の見切りをつけることにも役立つと思います。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;仕事も英語と同じように技術職なので、同じ手順を踏むことでより深いスキルが身につくことでしょう。これからは技術的な話題も、このサイトで取り扱っていきたいと思います。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-経済的自立&quot;&gt;4. 経済的自立&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;これは達成されました。経済的独立を最優先順位の目標として置いておいてよかったと思います。自立なしに二の次を言うな、という考え方は適切であったし、事業をする立場でもの、サービスの経済的側面を忘れざるべからずと自分への戒めになります。テスラへの応募を除き、本格的な就職活動は本の執筆が終わってから売れ行きや自分の動機、また塾講師での仕事などを吟味してから始めました。運が良かったことに、1 ヶ月強後の 10 月末には新卒としての内定を取得しました。企業は五万とあり、必ず採用口は見つかると思います。ポテンシャル採用の素晴らしいところとして、社会人 1 年目からその業界で仕事(または教育を受けながら)することができますので、これは活用しない手はありません。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;振り返ってみてやっておいたらよかったと思ったこと&quot;&gt;振り返ってみて、やっておいたらよかったと思ったこと&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;もし当時の自分と話せたら何をいうか、振り返っておきます。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;業界に関係なく、github の使い方を学んでおくべきでした。さまざまな使い道があるので、今後他の記事で取り扱おうと思います。&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;もっと技術書に頼って理論などを勉強するのではなく、作ってみて手を動かすこと。仕事でも結局インターネットでぶつ切りの情報を取って活用できるようになるまでに、体系立った基礎知識(仕事で使えるようになるまでの)を身につけなければいけませんが、これには本が 1 番良いと思います。&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;google 検索して質問の答えを探す練習。万事ものの効率が違いますし、検索もある種のスキルとして練習しておくと良いです。&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;公私共に、技術やスキルなどよりも人との巡り合わせほど支配的な要素はないと、リマインドしておきたいです。&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;石の上に三年いても石のまま、環境を変えることは悪いことではありません。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;総じてギャップイヤーを通してやっておいて良かったこと&quot;&gt;総じて、ギャップイヤーを通してやっておいて良かったこと&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;特に執筆した経験。自分の言葉で噛み砕くことでより深く使える知識が身につき、公私共にいろんなものに通じる基礎訓練になったと思います。&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;日々思っていることを書いて整理し、向き合うこと。自分を成長の比較対象にする時に大きく役立ちます。私は日記を活用してうまくいっていること、ないことを振り返っていました。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;これから&quot;&gt;これから&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;長くまで読んでいただきありがとうございました。ギャップイヤーを通して、一見世間からは必要とされないような小さな試行錯誤から、専門性の磨き方、失敗との向き合い方、自分にあったキャリアの考え方、公私双方で大切なことの発見、世間の大筋から外れることで起きた発見など、幅広く経験できたと思います。ギャップイヤーを取ることがもっと当たり前になってほしいし、他の経歴を辿った人がどのようなギャップイヤーを送るのか、ぜひともみてみたいと願ってやみません。&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>[{&quot;name&quot;=&gt;&quot;Daisuke Miyazaki&quot;}, {&quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;daisuke.miyazaki012@gmail.com&quot;}]</name></author><category term="jp" /><summary type="html">まず何よりも、私が初心に戻って振り返るため。また、当時(そしてきっと今も)前例が日本では少なかったし、当時ギャップイヤーを選択した人は周りに1人もいなかったため、キャリアの相談をすることできませんでした。そのためこの記事が、誰かの参考になればと思った次第です。</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Belongings</title><link href="https://mdaisuke.net/en/2021/05/12/belongings/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Belongings" /><published>2021-05-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-05-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mdaisuke.net/en/2021/05/12/belongings</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mdaisuke.net/en/2021/05/12/belongings/">&lt;p&gt;After reading &lt;a href=&quot;https://konmari.jp/&quot;&gt;The Life-Changing Magic of Tidying Up: The Japanese Art of Decluttering and Organizing&lt;/a&gt; from Marie Kondo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When embarking on a journey, what do people think about? Visiting unknown places, eating cuisines that they have never tasted, and getting in touch with histories and cultures of the place. They may discover something new, or be able to reflect on their footsteps in their life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When outing afar, you would get ready as your imagination and heart guide: choosing what to wear and what to use for your hobby, and putting them in your suitcase. For just a small stroll alone, it’s the same. You prepare well to make the trip comfortable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such items help you right by your side, all along with your journey as your company. Yes, your items want to be helpful to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Savoring the journey with the items selected with care and joy, excites you. You must feel your heart dancing. In the morning of a journey, you can’t help but to feel excited to wake up – you must have experienced something like this over and over again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, have a look around. If outside, it’s your clothes, cover case of the smart phone, and bag. If at home, it’s your decor, important T-shirt that your significant other gave to you, and favorite key holder and pen case with fond memories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must have unique stories and anecdotes that are interwoven between you and them. The fact that they exist there right by your side prove that you have such relationship with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your items and you live together. Why not sorting out your room, facing with items that bring you spark-joy, and taking care of them? The more items you have, the time you can spend with each shortens. As long as they are there, taking care of them from dusts is same as treating yourself right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this moment, your items – each one of them – wants to be helpful to you. Whenever you are feeling from stressed out to tired after a long day, your items always stay by your side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People are dynamic; your preferences and relationships would always change as your jobs, environment, and even yourself change. As this happens, naturally, what brings you spark-joy also changes. As people occasionally reflect on themselves, sometimes let yourself scrutinize and take care of your belongings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To start over with the outlook as Japanese says, one may buy new items to completely refresh the mind. Likewise, it’s possible to let go unnecessary items that don’t bring you any spark joy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When releasing your items, it should create some mental space and make you feel refreshed or reminiscent. You may feel comfortable, mentally uncluttered, or missing out, agitated. Either way, it’s meaningful to be aware of your emotions and to observe them. Because that is an important process that guides you to behave as your heart drives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you have the mental space, you can start planing what to do from there on. If leaving yourself in the mental space is comfortable, it’s alright to do so. Or, you could get on to something new too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clothings that were chosen to be yours in the ocean of items out there, express you. Kettles that change electric energy to hot water in a couple of minutes; Smart phones that deliver music to your ear anytime and anywhere, instead of having professional musicians play; Video services that interest you restlessly; they all enrich your life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We live in the civilization where advanced technologies are democratized. The cheaper, faster, and more convenient products and services are ever available to everybody than before; our day-to-day is filled with them and itself is the wealth that we all share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, mental spaces are disappearing from everybody. From advertisements that catch your eyes here and there, to the magical Internet temptation that sits in your pocket; everything around you does not stop drawing you to temptation at any time. So the question I’d like to pose is; does the mental space get to be erased by the wealth of items and services, or does it co-exist?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The motivation to create stuff lies in to embody a more convenient, easier, and richer lifestyle. Under this situation, our heart and passion comes ahead of materialistic objects. Probably since then, people started to grow a sense of attachment to or being drowned in the belongings as a result of the creation. Humans and items must have been living together since the born of the first civilization, so it can be said that we see citizens as bare humans and items combined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you can handle materialistic object like your limbs freely, humans can do a lot more. Originally, humans have evolved by using them – from the time with stones and furs, we’ve been accumulating and sophisticating items and eventually, we invented something that can do our work on behalf of us. As the beginning of computation era ends, its power distributed to individuals; as a result, &lt;a href=&quot;https://mdaisuke.net/blog/2020/01/20/daisuke-site-launched&quot;&gt;we live as cyborgs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I started taking care of my items and listening to how my heart drives, I’ve gotten to find the balance more at which the mental space and the wealth with items and services co-exist; that is, it’s a state of neither extreme minimalism nor extreme materialism. How to discover it is not something you’ll be told; instead, it may be something that each person needs to find on their own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since long time ago, grabbing attention has been beneficial for people. Now the driving force of competition to seek the benefit keeps accelerating. IoT devices like smart phones started to get to know your minds, and part of smart phones and services that have become magic have dissolved in your unconsciousness, sometimes nudging your mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because the world is going to change, this awareness that it’s an active act of discovering the balance will bring you a priceless mindset. Because the world is going to change, I want to recognize the changes of my mind with this mindset. I want to build a habit of listening to what my heart says and take care of my belongings with heart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because before any other of your belongings, it is the heart that is yours. If you don’t recognize its change, the peace of your mind – your heart – will probably be occupied immediately. Coincidentally in Japanese Chinese characters, being busy is written as ‘loosing heart’. Taking care of your belongings with heart will be your excellent guidance.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>[{&quot;name&quot;=&gt;&quot;Daisuke Miyazaki&quot;}, {&quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;daisuke.miyazaki012@gmail.com&quot;}]</name></author><category term="en" /><summary type="html">When embarking on a journey, what do people think about? Visiting unknown places, eating cuisines that they have never tasted, and getting in touch with histories and cultures of the place. They may discover something new, or be able to reflect on their footsteps in their life.</summary></entry></feed>